It's been a while since I've done a
cooking kit video where I've introduced
a new cooking kit. Now, I have a couple
different cooking kits that I'm going to
introduce you today. One of actually,
come to think of it, all three of these
cooking kits were gifts to me at one
point or another. Some were given to me
a long time ago, even before I made the
channel. Uh, some were given to me while
I was making the channel. But the focus
of today is kind of take you through a
history and an idea of what kind of
fuels and cooking kits to choose, give
show you some of the interesting ones
that I have that have been used by
campers and avid outdoors people for a
long time and uh so you can make your
your best judgment. Now, I think I'm
going to start off probably with this
one here. This is the very first cooking
kit video that I ever made on the
channel, and this is from the late
1800s. Now, this cooking kit, it's
probably uh made out of copper and then
it's been tinned. It has a fuel canister
like so. Now, I don't know if they
actually used the fuel canister itself
for the stove. I think it works better
because originally it came with just
this little alcohol burner, which does
all right. It's it's okay, but it takes
forever for it to cook. And really, all
it does is just get things up to a
simmer. um if you wait long enough it
can get it up to a boil, but it takes a
long time to get there. But whereas
using this and I fabricated a wick like
so, uh it works a little bit better than
just using this little one. But anyhow,
you got your
burner one way or the other, the
canister or this thing, and you put your
water, your soup, or what have you in
that, and then you're good to go. That's
that's it. So, it's a oneman for sure
cooking kit. Now, all these things can
just fit inside. Makes it rather
portable. Perfect for a late 19th
century outdoors person. As you can see,
it's got the windcreen. It's got places
for you to uh, of course, look in it,
make sure that it's still burning
because it is alcohol and you need dark
to see whether or not it's burning. And
you got this nice big port to light it.
Okay, so that's pretty effective. The
next one is the Theraos. Now, I love the
Theraos. This is probably This is
definitely my top two. It goes back and
forth between the press and mess kit and
this one cuz I think this one is
ingenious. It really does work as
advertised. The problem is the fuel
doesn't exist anymore because I guess
they got a little bit of a a match with
um Sterno, which is going to come up
here in a little bit. But they came up
with a an issue and they argued over
patents and stuff. But here you have
your cook kit. So you have one, two, and
your skillet to cook on top of. You put
your fuel, which was in this little cup.
This is not the original cup. And it has
a little canister that you put the fuel
in on this has plenty of little
perforations for the air flow to go
through and heat rises. So as you cook
the first one, heat is still rising up
and it's heating up the second one and
the third one. But the idea is that you
put the thing that you want to eat first
down below and as you get done cooking
that you drop the next one,
etc. So maybe you're getting your coffee
in this one and your beans in this one.
And then um maybe your eggs or bacon or
something else on the skillet, right?
But you want to drink your coffee. So
you heat up your coffee first while it's
cooling down, you have the next thing
that's heating up. And by the time that
that is done eating, that would be your
main course, right? Then you have your
secondary or vice versa, depending on
what you're eating and in what order,
you know? But I like how it all folds up
together into one nice convenient
package. One weird thing is this little
handle. I've shared that in a previous
video. I'll put um I'll put a list of
these videos in the description box. So
if you want to see them in order or
whatever, uh you can have take a look at
it because I do go in a lot more detail
even demonstrating their use in those
videos. So, that is the Theros mess kit.
Not to be confused with the Preston mess
kit, which by the way, if you're uh not
familiar with Preston mess kit, like I
said, it's my top two, I go between the
two, but it has your plate, has your
skillet, has your cup, and has your
canteen. It's all inclusive. And the
cool thing is like the plate and the
skillet can come together. It can create
a baking vessel or a containing vessel
for your viddles or what have you.
So, uh, if you want to, if you're
interested and get on the list for that,
in the description box below, there's a
link there's a video to it. It shows you
the history cuz the history is so cool.
But that is the Preston mess kit. And at
the end of this video, I'll actually
link it to that video because I'm trying
to get 500 people interested. Once we
get 500 people, we'll have the green
light to go and we'll start putting this
stuff into production and you can have
your own. They're rare. They're rare as
hens teeth. Even more rare than the
theos. The theos is also super uncommon
to find, but nonetheless, there you go.
All right, so we've got those. We're not
to the sterno yet. The next comes like
kerosene.
Like it, love it, hate it, whatever. The
kerosene stove
works really well. And kerosene actually
heats up hotter than what alcohol does.
So, um, it can be a little finicky to
play with at first, especially like the
older kerosene ones like this Primus,
but once you get it dialed in, they work
really well. I've got a larger one that
I'm seriously thinking about selling
because I can't get it to work and it's
so big, it's way more than what I
probably even need. So, uh, I got this
little small one, the 96 versus the 100.
And I like my 96. Smaller, lighter,
easier to pack away, and it works.
That's the best part is it works.
But it uses uh kerosene, not alcohol.
Sorry, meant to show you this when I was
showing you the alcohol stove. A lot of
people really like the alcohol stoves
because you can get this like can make
small rinky dink backpacking alcohol
stoves and just using two pop cans if
some scissors and you're good to go,
right? Uh, so alcohol is still a very
practical, modern source of cooking on
the backpacking trails. You can get big
gallons like this at your Lowe's or
hardware store. That's where I got mine.
Some people use heat because if you're
overseas, I guess denatured alcohol is
kind of hard to get for some reason. So,
people use heat over there. I've never
used heat. I've only used actual
denatured alcohol. This is not the same
alcohol that you use for like your first
aid purposes and certainly not the same
alcohol that you use to drink. So, don't
drink this and don't use this for first
aid. All right.
All right. Now, we're getting to
the stars of the show.
Before I get to the stars of the show
though, I'm going to jump ahead. I'm
going to talk about the Optimus. Now, I
like the Optimus stove. This thing is
heavy for a backpacking stove, but it's
all inclusive and it uses white gas. I
like the Optimus more than I would like
any of these other ones. When I go
backpacking, when I go uh camp outs or
whatever, I always take this with me. It
is heavy compared to like modern
backpacking stoves, especially like
Whisper Lights and stuff like that. But
I like how simple it is. It has the
priming pump that came with it. You can
buy an extra one if you don't have one,
but it comes with the priming pump. It
works effectively. It's reliable. I
don't need to take alcohol to prime it
like I do with the kerosene stoves or
other things. Um, white gas is getting
harder to get in some places. I haven't
had a trouble with it yet, but I seen
that the prices are going up on white
gas. Uh, I like my white gas camping
stoves, you know, the old Coleman's. I
also like my white gas lanterns. I know
the government and companies are trying
to phase those out in uh favor of things
that they could sell themselves. Like
you got to buy those fuel canisters for
the propane um anymore. So I like white
gas.
Now let's get to Sterno. I have two
examples of Sterno Stows. Now these are
the Sterno canisters, also known as
shafing fuel. This is not the same
recipe as they used to use back in the
early 1900s when they first came out.
Back in the early 1900s, Sterno
exploded. There was a lot of people
using Sterno as fuel. You've got like
the Theros company that was in arguments
back and forth with them about using a
similar fuel. But Sterno today does not
heat up as hot as the old Sterno.
Doesn't cook as well. Long story short,
it does a good job of getting things up
to maybe a a simmer or it can take a
long time to get it bubbling and
actually boiling. I have seen it in the
right conditions, but in winter
conditions, no. Sterno just doesn't work
in winter conditions. Summer conditions,
sure, like you can heat up some food uh
and it does a pretty decent job, but not
in so much winter conditions. Now, what
I have, this was given to me by one of
my viewers and Facebook friends and
everything. Warren, he had this and he
asked me if I'd be interested in it. He
sent it to me as uh, you know, just as
my efforts trying to educate people
about camping and the outdoors, and I
greatly appreciate it cuz I didn't know
anything like this existed.
So, as you can tell, Sterno fuel
canisters used to be a fraction of the
size. He sent me
this can, too. So, I could cut it and it
fits just right um to work on something
like this. So, if I cut this out or
maybe crimp it down or something like
that, and I use this by putting the
sterno inside of it and see how it
works, which we will at a different
video, but this is just kind of a primer
video showing you the history of various
camping stoves that I have. So, anyhow,
very small, very small canisters back in
the day. And this would rest on that
canister. And you would even have this
handy dandy little paddle here to
extinguish it, which is cool. Just like
using the lid on your sterno cans today.
So instead of blowing it out or
something like that, you just put that
out and it automatically extinguishes.
Then you have this pot, which this pot
is very reminiscent
of this late 1800's one. As you can see,
it's got the butterfly handles that are
so prevalent in uh, you know,
mid-century, early 20th century camping
vessels. In fact,
I even have this one, which is made out
of 10. I don't know what stove or what
this went with, but same thing. Nice big
size pretty much. Oops.
Not quite. It's a little bit bigger.
than the aluminum one. So, this is
aluminum. They sold these up until the
1950s, these Sterno things. Uh, but they
were around as early as the 19 late
1920s from different advertisements that
I've seen. So, this is pretty cool. A
nice little uh kit just to do what you
need to do. Of course, if there was
liquid in there, it' be more balanced.
And you have this very thin aluminum
lid. It doesn't sit on there very tight,
but it'll still do the job that it needs
to do to help things uh heat up a little
bit faster.
So, that is that old school
Sterno stove. Everything packs into that
pot, which is always handy when you're
going backpacking. Next is this. This is
probably like 1980s,
1990s.
This is also a Sterno stove. And if
you've been around camping long enough,
I pretty much guarantee
you've seen these.
Try to show it so you can see how it
works. But you got a little wire here
and you got little hooks. So that just
kind of bends in there, bends in, bends
in and locks into place. So that holds
it. And you got this little door. You
have your sterno can
and you put it right in there and it
sits dead center. You close up that door
to try to maintain the heat. This is
very thin aluminum, heavy gauge
aluminum, but it's it's aluminum.
And you have your cooking vessel on top.
There you go. That is the late 1980s,
maybe 1970s. I think I've seen
advertisements for these 1970s as well,
but pretty much 1980s, 1990s Sterno
backpacking stove.
All right. Now, those scouts, scouts out
there, they sold these even in the 1990s
when I was a scout. Uh, I have no idea.
Actually, I do have an idea when this
one was made. This was made in the 1950s
because it says Boy Scouts of America,
National Council, New York City. So,
this is an old one. Uh, patented
Milwaukee, USA Corporation,
uh, JW
speaker on the back of it. I didn't know
these things were that old. I This is
like the first time I actually analyzed
that stamp. So, I didn't realize this
was from the 1950s. I thought this was
much newer. Like I said, they had these
even when I was a scout in the 90s.
So, you have this aluminum container.
Inside of it is
a cardboard box. If I can get it out.
Uh, I don't want to ruin it.
Don't want to tear it up.
Come on. Come on. Get out. All right.
You have these little heat tabs. These
are very similar to the heat tabs that
the military used uh even in Vietnam.
And when I was a kid, we had this uh GI
uh depot place that had like surplus
gear and stuff. They used to sell
military tabs. And my gosh, as a scout,
those things were so awesome to either
cook with or start a fire with cuz they
light right up and they would be blue
and hot. boy, you could do anything with
them. So, let me uh move the camera so
you can take a look at this.
So, here you go. This is the uh this is
the tab. See how small they are? So, you
get a bunch of them. This has never been
used. I'm not going to light one for you
because well, that wouldn't be very uh
historical of me to do that. And you can
kind of see here 101 uses speaker heat
tabs trademark register tablets or
concentrated heat of concentrated heat
fry heat or boil.
Outdoors use large size heat tabs for
hunting, fishing, starting campfires,
emergency sterilization, etc. Indoors
small use small size heat tabs for
heating baby's milk. Quick hot water for
shaving. Sick room heating coffee
anywhere, bedside uses, etc. Two hours
of heat in this box. Isn't that cool?
I don't know if I can uh show you that.
When you buy refills of heat tabs,
specify
of 24 heat tabs, large size or package
of 24 heat tabs, medium size by the
speaker core. There you go.
That cool.
Isn't that cool?
You kind of see what they look like up
close.
So, these were sold to scouts. Like I
said, they had these when I was a kid.
Uh I I got to play around with them when
I was a kid, and they worked really
well. Surprisingly well. And as always
with hunting or camping gear, I love how
small it all packs down. So, as you
bring this up, you've got your air
circulation coming through. There's
holes there. So again, you got your air
circulation. Then you take your Boy
Scout mess kit, I'm sure, and you put
over top of it. And there you go. You
got your stove right there. I mean, that
is that is small, right? Like that's
that's pretty cool. When you're thinking
about backpacking
or long-distance trekking, saving
weight, this this is the ideal, right? I
know they got like those fire boxes you
can put sticks in. I know we got our
whisper lights and stuff like that, but
if you could have just some heat tabs
and one or two heat tabs could cook your
meal,
that's pretty sweet. These things weigh
a lot less than having liquid. You think
about like you know 5 lb 10 lb um of
fuel to really take care of you know a
whole group of people whereas each
person just has something like this 24
heat tabs then that will take care of
you for the entire weekend for sure. All
right.
So, there you go, my friends. That is my
collection. And I think I have a few
more. And uh if you're interested in the
press and mess, then check out the
description box below because this thing
is so cool. Like I said before, you've
got your skillet
like so. You've got your plate, you've
got your cup, which all folds down. See
the handle on there? And you got your
canteen all together, right? It's in the
description box below. We need 500
people to make this thing a reality. I'd
love it if you join us. Also, I want to
invite you. There's a limited number of
spots available at the Camp Crafters
Guild Squirrel Camp. Now, in October
from it's a 4-day squirrel camp, right?
From October 22nd to the 26th. You leave
on Sunday the 26th, right? By 11. Um
they're at Dave Canter's property in
southeastern Ohio. He's hosting us for
the second annual squirrel camp. And if
you don't want to hunt, you can just c
come and camp in historic, you know,
garb and equipment. You do have to have
period equipment and garb to participate
because this is a full immersive
experience. If you've ever wanted to
experience an old school early 20th
century hunting camp, this is where you
can do it. So, it's really unique from
other reenactments or living histories
because this is truly an immersive
camping experience. You're cooking just
like they did in the mid well early 20th
century. You're sleeping in the early
20th century. You're dressed in the
early 20th century. And you're hunting
just like you would in the early 20th
century. So, if you have that kind of
kit or if you're wanting to get one of
those kits together, which will help
you, right? will guide you in the right
direction and everything to start your
journey. Then join us at the second
annual Camp Crafters Guild Squirrel Camp
hosted by Dave Canterberry uh the
Pathfinder School. Now, a cool thing is
once you register, it costs $10. It's
just a small $10 and that's going to pay
for your freebies that you get
participating cuz we're going to give
you some things to try to enhance the
experience. Uh, so it's $10
registration. You get locked into a very
exclusive part of the Camp Crafters
Guild where you can share, you know,
what you have, your plans, questions,
research, etc. Other members are on
there that post what they have. It's
just a great collaborative experience.
It be a lot of fun. If you don't like
cooking, Sarge Van is going to be there
and so is Josh Wilson. put their YouTube
channels below in the description box,
but they're going to be there and
they're going to be our camp cooks and
Sarge has already got something awesome
planned for those guys who are actually
hunting and going out to have their
lunch out while they're hunting and
having a camp lunch. Uh so you can
participate in that if you so choose. is
an additional charge, but it will be a
true immersive camp cook hunting camp
experience that uh I know you enjoy. But
it's limited to 25 people. So, if you
want to be one of those 25 people, you
need to get locked in now and uh don't
wait till the last minute because last
year, you know, we had almost 25 people.
We weren't there quite yet, but we
almost had 25 people and they got first
invite. Since they came last year, they
got invitation to take up spots that are
now available for this year. And uh
that's just how we'll do it. So if you
come, then you will pretty much be
locked in to your invite the following
year. And the cool thing about that is
you uh if you've ever been to a living
history event, you see the same people
over and over again. you build a like a
family type feeling and it's a just an
incredible
it's an incredible experience. It really
is when you get to go to reenact and you
see some of the familiar uh faces and
you're sharing some stories. You know,
you might not see each other but once or
twice a year. Um it's just it's cool. So
check it out. Camp Crafters Guild at
Dave Canberry's property. Don't forget
to check out the description box below
for the link for the Preston mess kit.
If you like the video, please click
like. We always appreciate that. If you
don't like it, that's fine. I'd love to
hear your guys' stories about what kind
of either collection you have, maybe
your favorite cooking set with fuel,
okay? I'm not talking about like the Boy
Scout mess kit. Talking about an actual
cooking set that has uh the place for
the fuel or you have a favorite
backpacking stove or what have you. uh
some old stories that you have because I
love reading your guys' stories and I
know other people really enjoy it as
well. So, put that in the comments
below. You can always reach out to me
with any questions. You can join us at
the Camp Crafters Guild
w.oniblefitters.com/jointheguild.
There is a free segment on there that is
open to everybody. You can come on check
it out. There's a lot of really cool
spots and resources that are available
for the free side. But if you want to
dive into the more advanced side, then
check out the paid side because the paid
side has a lot more to it. All right, if
you'd like to see the video about the
press and mess kit, then check it out
here. If you'd like to see the video of
all my other camp crafting videos, then
check it out here. Hope you guys have a
wonderful week. Give a kiss to your
loved ones and I'll see you guys next
time. Take care.