And the handle pulls out. Kind of snaps
in place. And it has right here on the
rear. Now it's completely sealed. And we
have a little oven.
Hello. Welcome to Waypoint Survival.
Today we're going to talk about Horus
Keart's amazing cook kit. Stay tuned.
Sometime in the 1890s, a gentleman by
the name of Guy Preston invented this
messkit cook kit canteen combination.
Now, this was a special purchase item.
As far as we know, it was never an issue
item to the army. Of course, I'm sure he
wanted that to happen, but this was
picked up and sold to officers perhaps,
uh, people that had some money because
this was expensive even back in the day,
but purchased by their families perhaps
before they went off to war. So, this
would have been predating the Spanishame
War of 1898 and then on into the early
1900s. And this was sold even by
Abbercrombie and Fitch on into the
1920s. I'm not sure when they stopped
selling it, but this is a very difficult
item to get a hold of. Now, Horus Kart
had one of these. And as a matter of
fact, if you look in the museum that has
the remainder of his stuff, you will
find this in his kit items. The clues
that we have as to what he carried is
now housed at the Western Carolina
University. And they have all of the
items that were left. Mr. Keepart
unfortunately died in 1931 in a car
accident. One of his good friends, I
think a lawyer, uh something like that,
had these items. They were in storage
for a while and ultimately they end up
being donated to the university and you
can go online and you can find pictures
of them. But this is one of the things
that he had and carried. Now, Horus
Keart, like a lot of us modern survival
bushcraft guys, uh we test different
gear items and we don't know if he
purchased this or if this was sent to
him. I think it was sent to him, but he
did enjoy it. He did like it and he
wrote well about it. So, I managed to
get a hold of one of these and as part
of the Camplike Kart series, I'm going
to show you what this is like. Now,
there's a special thing that's coming up
where you may be able to purchase one of
these. So, stay tuned to the end of the
video so I can give you that
information. One of the things that you
notice when you first get one of these
kits is that it's kind of an unusual
configuration. Now, there are many
different types of carriers that these
came with or that were made for them and
probably would depend on who is the
retailer and even if someone would have
a private individual make one for them.
Now, this particular holder here was
sold by Abberrombi and Fitch. And for
those of you who don't know,
Abberrombian Fitch was the premier
retailer of outdoor accessories for the
serious sportsman. So, it wasn't just a
yepy clothing store as it is today. And
now I'd like to thank the sponsor of
today's video, Mave. Whether we're out
on the trail or just sitting around a
campfire, my dog isn't just a companion.
He's like family. And just like I'm
serious about what I put in my body,
it's good to want the same level of care
for him back at home. Mave isn't your
typical dog food. It's raw, human-grade,
nutrient-rich food designed to give your
dog everything they need to thrive.
Whether they're a wilderness cruiser
like mine or just your everyday couch
buddy, it comes frozen to lock in
freshness. Just scoop it straight from
the freezer or you can let it thaw for a
few minutes. What I really love about
it, Mave has thought of everything from
their daily vitamin bars, which my dog
devours just like a treat, to their bone
broth toppers, which you can add for an
extra nutritional boost. This isn't just
food. It's a complete system for K9
health. It's crafted to support seven
key areas of my dog's well-being. Oral
health, weight and digestion, immunity,
anxiety, joints, skin and coat. It even
helps with proper puppy development.
With Mave, your dog will definitely want
to be part of the Clean Bowl Club. So,
if you're ready to take your dog's
health as seriously as your own, check
out the link in the description box
below or scan the QR code that's been
showing on your screen to check out Mave
because your best friend deserves the
best fuel for all of life's adventures.
All right, let's get into this. So,
you'll notice that there's kind of a sho
string, a cord here that holds this
open, and then it's just a series of
speed laces
that unwinds here. You can take this
like that and then we can access the
kit.
Of course, you'll notice immediately
that there's a canteen here and it was
sealed with just a cork.
Removing that, we look inside here and
we can see that it is lined with felt
and this is to insulate it in the winter
time. But you could also soak this in
the water and this would through
evaporation and evaporational cooling it
would help keep your canteen water cool.
The way this particular bag is made and
if you want to see the old Abberrombie
and Fitch label,
there it is.
But the way that this bag is made, you
can pull this felt back and there is an
angled pocket down inside and there is
enough room for a fork and a spoon.
So again, down inside
and it fits in there quite securely. And
then when you put this on, then it
protects it from rattling around in your
gear. Pretty ingenious. And then this is
just a cotton type strap. It does look
like it's been repaired perhaps or
shortened at some point in its life.
There's a repair right there. And uh
still in pretty good shape though. It is
a waxed canvas. And I do like that about
it. Next, we get into the heart of the
matter, which is what makes this kit so
unique.
It has a clamshell type arrangement on
either side.
So you can see that
the canteen rides in the middle. Has a
little bit of a divot here. Now these
also came with what was called a half
canteen. So the canteen was only half
the size. And that would allow you to
put a little bit of food down in the
bottom if you want. But I would have
probably even back in the day preferred
the full length canteen. And these were
tinned. And so many of these, as you can
see, this one has rust on it. Many of
them rusted very badly. They were
soldered together with uh solder that
more than likely had lead in it. Uh this
one has had a significant amount of
repairs done to it where it had rusted
through and started leaking. So really
this is more for looks. Now I do have a
replacement one that's made from copper
that I got from the gentleman when I
bought this kit and uh it is good enough
to carry water in. But this one right
here is really just to keep it original.
Now this is the cup or the pot and the
canteen nests in it. So, we'll set that
to the side. And this has some unique
features. If you look down inside, you
can see that is the handle. And the
handle pulls out. Kind of snaps in
place. And it has right here on the rear
something that rotates. Okay? See that?
So, you put this on the flat. You pull
this over. And then you would spin that.
And that locks that into place so that
we can now cook over the fire. Has a
somewhat of a flat bottom so it sets.
Okay. But this is really unique and it's
big enough that this is going to hold a
decent sized can of beans or whatever
you're uh cooking pork and beans
perhaps. And that's a really unique
feature. Uh it's very easy to handle.
And this kit is made from aluminum in
case you were wondering. The next item,
the first part of the clam shell is your
plate. And it's got a little bit of a a
loop here. You see you can little ring
so you can hang that up if you want to
dry it. And then it's got a place for a
pin on the other side. Get to that in a
minute.
The other half of the clamshell is your
frying pan. So, here's the handle. This
opens up like this. And there is right
here a little sliding pin. So, when you
open this up like this, there's a hole
right here. This slides into there.
Pushes down and locks into place. It's
nice and sturdy. And this is a handy
dandy frying pan. I mean, it's a good
size. It's deep enough that you can fry
eggs or bacon or anything like that for
breakfast and it will do a really good
job of that. Now, there's something else
that this kit does that makes this so
unique and so worth having. So, if we
take this pin and pull this back out, so
the handle rotates on the frying pan,
we've got this square ring right here.
And you'll notice that there's a hook.
This hooks onto that just like this.
And then this goes down inside
just like that.
And it nests inside the top pan.
Now, these can be a little bit difficult
to get together because of their age.
Once you get that in place, then the pin
should go ahead and push in right here.
Just like that. Now it's completely
sealed and we have a little oven. We can
use this to bake our bread. And I just
think that is super clever. You can also
use this to store food long term. Let's
say you're leaving camp and you want to
just stick this in your pack. There's
plenty of room uh in your backpack for
that hopefully. But in here, there's
absolutely no problem with carrying just
the canteen and the cup or the pot. Snap
that back into place. This goes in.
We close this up and then this becomes
your extra food storage. Of course,
nothing that would leak or run or
anything like that. But you could see
making some trail bread or some
cornbread or something like that and
just keeping this for later would be
just extremely convenient. Putting the
whole kit back together is super simple.
Again, we just nest this.
We put this on one side and this on the
other. Just like that. And that's it.
goes back inside the bag. It's got your
silverware. It's got your oven. It has
your plate, your frying pan. And because
of the way that it's made with the mouth
of the canteen being exposed above the
whole kit, it's an easy thing to open
that up and drink from it. So, works
perfectly as a canteen during the day.
When you stop for camp or for the
afternoon for a meal, everything's right
to hand. It's easily accessible. It
doesn't weigh a whole lot. And I can
just see this is a a phenomenal piece of
gear. It's no wonder Horus Kart liked
it. And now for some great news. A lot
of the kits and the gear that I show you
are almost impossible to find. This is
extremely rare in today's world, and I
don't think that there was a whole lot
of them sold back in the day, which is
why so few of them have existed down to
modern times.
However, my friend, Mr. Sha Dyer of the
Honorable Outfitters, Mr. Dyer's
Musings, and I'll make sure and put his
channel link down in the description box
as well. He wants to reproduce these.
Now, it'll be in 318 stainless steel, so
not aluminum. Again, we know there could
be problems with aluminum, especially
buildup over time. So, it's going to be
in a good grade of stainless steel. He's
planning to take this, he's got a couple
of originals himself, and he's going to
take it to Columbus, Ohio, and he's
going to have a company there scan it,
and they're going to reproduce this.
You're going to do 500 of them. Now,
these are not going to be cheap. They
weren't cheap in the beginning, but the
reproductions are going to cost $175.
Now, I know that sounds like a lot, but
this is a chance to get something that
is absolutely unique in the outdoor
world. And if you like doing reenacting,
this is definitely something that you
want to have in your kit. There are a
couple things to know about the kit that
he is reproducing. First of all, it
won't have a cork that's not really
secure. It's going to have an internal
frid. Now, if he gets enough orders and
he goes to a second run, he said there's
a possibility he may reproduce some that
are exactly like the original, but for
our modern use, probably a screw cap
would be a lot better. Now, the
reproduction kit, not only will it have
a screw top lid, but will also come with
the frying pan, the plate, the canteen,
and then the canteen cup or pot just as
you see it here. They're going to try to
reproduce it as faithfully as possible.
Again, the only exception being no cork,
a nice screw top lid. The kit will not
come with any kind of a carrier. But Mr.
Dyer said for all of the early
responders, he'll make sure and include
two different patterns where you can
make your own or if you know someone
that can sew, they can make it for you.
That was very common back in the day.
And I know that a lot of you reenactors,
you make your own gear anyway, so it's
not going to be that hard for you. But
anyway, that's nice. a couple of
different patterns of the ones that he
has. Now, there is a time constraint on
this. He needs to have the answer in the
next two days by July 16th, 2025. And I
will make sure and put that link down in
the description box where you can go
there and you can sign up to get one of
these. Now, the $175 is not due right
away, but he does want to get that
payment by August 1st. That $175
does include shipping to the Continental
48 United States. Now, if you live
outside that or you live in some other
part of the world, you can contact Mr.
Dyer. Again, the link will be down below
where you can contact him and he's going
to keep us updated on the progress of
this kit. Now, as many of you as can, we
really need you to jump on board and
order one of these if you can at all
afford it. This would make a fantastic
Christmas gift or birthday present or
just a whatever kind of present for
someone that you know that loves the
outdoors. Basically, nobody has these
and almost all of them are really old
and the cantens are just not in usable
shape. So, getting a fresh run of them
is a real benefit to us in the outdoor
world. Mr. Dyer is trying to get at
least 500 people to sign on for this so
it can make it economically viable to
actually reproduce. And if he gets
enough of those, then we're going to go
into production, charge the rate, and it
could take up to a year to get these
reproduced, but it's likely going to be
a lot sooner. Again, it just depends on
the market and what happens and and how
backed up the factory is and all of that
that's actually reproducing this in the
318 stainless steel. However, because
Mr. Dyer will have your contact
information, he's going to keep us all a
breast of the progress as this is
produced all the way down to shipping
them out. So, I'm really looking forward
to this and as a matter of fact, I am
planning on getting one, of course, and
I'm really looking forward to using it.
I love these old kits. It looks great in
my series, but because it is an antique
and because they are rare, we have to be
super careful with them. So, needless to
say, I'm pretty pumped about getting a
new one that I can actually take out and
use in the woods. Well, folks, I hope
you've enjoyed this video. Another fora
into the past, another one in our series
of camping like Keepart. This is an
amazing cook kit. I'm glad that I was
able to get a hold of one of the
originals, but again, as I said before,
I'm really excited to get the
reproduction rolling. So, help me get
down there, click on those sites, sign
up for this. Let's get this thing back
into production. This is James Bender
for Waypoint Survival. If you like this
video, please give it a thumbs up. Also,
make sure and check out the links in the
description box below just under the
more button. While you're there, you'll
find the link where you can get on the
list to purchase one of these amazing
cook kits that is being reproduced by
Mr. Dyer. As I told you previously, all
the information will be in that link.
Now, you need to do so by July 16th.
That's this coming Wednesday, 2025.
Also, in the description box, you'll
find the link for our Waypoint Survival
Digital Class. And this is where you can
sign up to train in the comfort and
convenience of your own backyard, the
top 20 skills that we consider to be the
most important from our phase 1 survival
and bushcraft class. You'll also find
the waypoint survival.com link, and this
is where you can sign up to come and
take in-person classes here at our
beautiful training facility in southern
Ohio. And if you haven't already done
so, please subscribe to the channel.
We'd really appreciate it. And when you
do subscribe, make sure and press that
bell button so that you can stay
notified of all of our upcoming videos.
And we'll talk to you next time.
[Music]
[Applause]