If you think we only think with our
brains, you tend to see AI as a
replacement of our thinking process. We
use AI to think for us instead.
And that's obviously a risk. And if you
think like that, you do that. You stop
thinking for yourself. You let AI do the
work.
Mind Hack is a podcast about the
psychology behind performance, behavior
change, and self-optimization.
Each episode explores how to think
clearly, work smarter, and live
intentionally through insightful
conversations with leading
entrepreneurs, scientists, and experts
in human behavior.
Hello and welcome to the Mind Hack
Podcast, the show where we explore the
science of peak performance, mindset,
and personal growth. I'm your host Cody
Mlan and today I'm joined by Dr. Sank
Arn, a distinguished social social
scientist, educator, and author of the
groundbreaking bestseller, How to Take
Smart Notes. His book, which introduced
the powerful Zettocast method of
personal knowledge management to over
100,000 readers worldwide, has
fundamentally challenged some of the
traditional views on how we learn,
think, and write. Dr. Rens argues that
writing is not just a way to document
our thoughts. It is the act of thinking
itself. A concept that has profoundly
reshaped my own approach to intellectual
work. In this conversation will
demystify the zetocasten approach often
described as building a second brain and
explore its practical power in
overcoming common intellectual
roadblocks like writer's block,
procrastination, and information
overload. We'll also discuss how Dr. RN
sees modern tools like Obsidian and
artificial intelligence fitting into the
future of effective note-taking and
learning. By the end of this episode,
you'll walk away with clear, actionable
insights and relatable strategies that
you can apply immediately, whether
you're looking to enhance academic
performance, streamline your research
process, or spark novel ideas for your
next major creative project. So, without
further ado, please welcome Dr. Shank
Ar.
>> Thank you, Cody, for having me.
>> Dr. Arves, welcome to the show. So, your
your book, How to Take Smart Notes, it's
resonated with so many people around the
world. You've sold over 100,000 copies.
You've translated into eight languages.
Did you ever expect your book on taking
notes would become so widespread?
>> Um, I had two thoughts. one is hopefully
I sell a few more than uh 10 copies and
I have I had mainly my own students in
mind because I couldn't find a really
helpful book on writing and notetaking
that mirrors the way I thought we
developed a thesis. So there was just
a need to write that because I didn't
feel comfortable with the ones that were
available. I did not expect at all that
it resonated so much with people outside
of academia. And
um I'm very pleased how people took
ideas and developed their own systems
around it. So I see it less as an
instruction and more as something that
sparked a discussion. I'm really glad um
happening. Yeah.
>> And so for those who haven't read your
book, can you give us kind of an
immediate idea about what it's about and
what kind of benefits that say new
adopters could expect to to learn from
your method?
>> Yeah, I mean there are multiple ways to
describe what the tetra cousin is all
about. Um, one way is it's um a system
to write
notes that connect in a way that you can
build something out of them and where
you have as you called it the second
brain or an external brain you're in a
dialogue with. Another way to describe
it and that's how I did it in the book
is um the author and social scientist
Nicholas Luman I studied the most um
he's a system theory thinker um he was
incredibly productive um writing almost
60 books and less than 30 years hundreds
of articles
and
um whenever he was was asked um how on
earth he was able to be that productive
um he referred to his subtle cousin. So
obviously uh as someone who struggled a
lot with writing I was intrigued uh what
this system is all about and there is a
research project still going on because
it's such a vast amount of notes that
needs to be digitalized and um
put online. Um
but there was very little available uh
at that time. Um but there are others
who work with similar methods and
so I tried to understand
um how that really worked in a practical
manner and
that was fascinating to me and um so I
wanted to write about that because there
wasn't anything available that really
described the method and because I at
the same time taught a lot about
um learning theories, I realized
how much the settle casten put modern
research into practice without lumen
probably being aware of that. Um but
and thirdly it resonates with um a new
line of research
that often
goes under the label of external
thinking. So the
realization how much of our environment
contributes
to our thinking processes and how much
we can do
to
improve our thinking by thinking a
little bit more systematically about how
we design our environment in which we
think. Um, so in a way it's all about
a thinking environment design. And
that might sound complicated, but in the
end it's just
writing on a daily or regular basis
small pieces
and add them to the existing
pool of ideas you have. So you extend
your thoughts instead of just collecting
them. And that
nudges you to
develop more complex thoughts because
having the thoughts externalized allows
you to build up complexity which is
impossible in our tiny brain. And it
also constantly confronts you with
things you have long forgotten.
And that is like a builtin
um critical element to your daily
writing. Um where you're being reminded
of things that might be um contradictory
to your great idea you had in the
morning. and instead of just putting it
out um you contrast that with something
you have already written down. And
these are the moments usually where
something interesting happens where you
have contradicting ideas and have to
figure out well um is one of them wrong
or can I um combine them in in a way.
Um, all these things only happen when
you have a system in place where you
have your thoughts in some way
externalized. And usually we do that
with books and articles all that is
external to our brain. But what we then
do we usually just do in our brain. So
it's like brain and the external
environment and that seat custom expands
the personal thinking space
to be able to think within that and I
think that's why Lumman was able to not
only be so proficient in his writing but
also be able to develop incredibly
complex thoughts and theories that are
highly consistent um within its itself
uh something that
that wouldn't be possible I think
without a system like that.
>> Right. So there's this other thing I'm
sure you're you're aware of called the
commonplace book. it's it's been famous
in history for for many writers,
Benjamin Franklin
included, is that they they created a
commonplace book where they would note
different references, quotes, ideas that
they would kind of keep with them for
the rest of their lives and that was
always an important part of their
writing process. Would you say that the
zodoccasted method is kind of like a
more complex version of that where
instead of just writing ideas, you're
also connecting
related thoughts?
>> I think it's
certainly um fits into the same category
of trying to use external means to
accompany you and um not just write
something down, put it out, and then go
back to the blank page.
But the settle cousin is certainly more
geared towards continuous development of
ideas and maybe less of a reminder um
and
um
I mean it's grounded in academia but
seeing how much it resonated outside of
academia I think it can be seen as um
maybe a little bit more sophisticated
version of the commonplace book. But you
tell me um you know better I think the
uh distinction between these two
systems.
No, I I would certainly say it's a more
nuanced complex version of a commonplace
book and yet it's also more difficult to
maintain and that's where certain
systems like Obsidian and other like
Rome have kind of come out in many of
the past few years to try to make it
easy to uh create these relationships
between different ideas. in doing so
kind of automatically but in the process
I think they also eliminate your own
intentional connection between these
ideas that perhaps is kind of removes
some of the critical thinking behind
making these connections yourselves uh
because I think there's this aspect of
what you argues you say in the book
writing is not just a record of thought
but the act of thinking itself and so
you argue that this method is a way for
you to to think about these things and
it's it's commonly notated that
obviously thinking about something
whether you're listening to an audio
book whether you're you're reading
something is that we we often don't
remember 95% of what we read in a book
but it's those moments when you come
across an idea you pause and you think
about that thought you think about it
from a different angle you think about
how does this apply to my life you you
expand on that idea those are the types
of things that we tend to remember and
so when you're taking that that kind
that instinctual part where you're
stopping and you're thinking about
something and you're adding it to a
system, then you can look at that and
expand on that further. And so I think
that certainly writing and note-taking
plays an active part of thinking. Um and
so I think everything has its place. Um
but um going off of going on a tangent,
uh do you have any additional thoughts
on top of that? Yeah, I think you strike
an important point and um let me comment
on the role of technology like obsidian
Rome research etc. Um I think there is
the risk that you do exactly what you
just said. Um automate the building of
connection and therefore just skip the
important step of thinking about what
connections make most sense
intellectually or by reasoning. But I
think this kind of technology doesn't
have to
um be used in that way. I think that
technology can
um complement
um our thinking very well if we are
aware of the risk you mentioned um that
we try to use it in a way that that it
skips the thinking part. I think when
you use Obsidian or Rome research or
lock and the other tools out there that
have the birectional linking feature,
um
you get quickly overwhelmed with links
when you automate that process or just
go by association like um oh this word
appears in these notes So I link them
all and I have uh beautiful graphs with
a lot of links
that can work as a warning signal. um
this overwhelming interconnectedness.
Um if you encounter that once, I think
you're thrown back to
uh the inside that any links should be
deliberate
and
ideally
commented on. Um so one of the main uh
points I keep stressing when I teach the
method is try to embed links to other
notes in full sentences. Try to explain
the relation between two notes in a way
that your future self can still
understand that. Um don't try to just um
have bullet points with um links.
They have their place as well, but the
main links should be explained to
yourself. And usually this is the moment
where you start thinking u because
intuitively often um the relation
between two pieces of information is
obvious. um you feel yeah of course this
belongs together but when you try to
make it explicit
you start to struggle and that is
usually the good kind of struggle. Um
first of all you might be right and then
it's good to be able to explain it
because in the end your knowledge isn't
much worth if you're not able to
communicate it. um if you can't tell
someone else how two things belong to
each other.
But most often you realize that
you haven't really thought through um
how two pieces of information belong
together and that you need more
information to make the connection um
plausible. So I think this linking which
can be done mostly automatic
uh if you do it manually where you feel
okay um it's interesting here
can zoom in
the most interesting parts of of what
you're doing. So I think the linking is
not a
support or help. I think it's often the
most important part of the whole process
and the most interesting
>> right and I I would in a easier way of
describing that I think if we look at
say if you are a surgeon and then
perhaps on the side you're you also like
to paint um or you you're in some other
completely unrelated field and it's
often the the people who end up in a
multitude of fields that have interests
and they're able to take those ideas and
overlap them with this other other
profession and that's often where we
have innovations and we have ideas that
kind of further society along because
you have overlapping uh knowledge in
different industries and so I think
these this idea of linking notes it's
kind of like a similar way of you're
you're creating this this this link
between notes and thoughts that perhaps
otherwise could be unrelated. It's
forcing yourself to think about a a
specific idea in a different way instead
of just looking at it in a in a linear
way, which is so often what we do,
especially when we're just creating
bullet points. when if if we have
highlights on a book, you know, we're
we're putting it into a specific
category and then we put, you know, if
it's a category on productivity, all all
of these notes might just just be in
this one one category, but there's
inevitably related I philosophical
ideas, industry ideas that you could
think about and that could be what
allows you to have kind of new creative
thinking and to write and and think from
a different perspective than most other
people would. Yeah, I think the art is
to
um find the right
level of abstraction.
Um on a two abstract um level everything
is related. And
if you try to find the
uh the abstraction level where two
uh until now unconnected pieces of
information can be put together. Um you
you create something new and
especially when you work
interdisciplinary and into very
different fields like medicine and art.
um you need to go to a more abstract
level but then also to respppecify
um from that level down to have a
concrete example or uh application of
that idea. I think that's where models
are extremely useful and have their
place because models are always
abstractions from reality but they
extremely useful uh because they are not
that abstract that you can't do anything
with them anymore. You can reapply them
on a more concrete level. Um,
yeah, sometimes people shy away a little
bit from too abstract ideas or abstract
ideas, but I think it's often
unavoidable to go that step to go back
um to a more concrete level in a
different field.
Um, yeah, that that's certainly what's
getting interesting.
>> Yeah. And and so you also say that notes
are only as valuable as the system that
they're embedded in. And so from a
perspective of of building a zetocasten
system, I know that we we touched on
Obsidian and Rome and u I believe uh
Lumen, you know, he he had these index
cards, right? And so he was able to
write over 60 books, uh hundreds of
articles, and he had like I think some
90,000 index cards. And there's a very
specific method of of putting like
notations in the upper right hand corner
to to link like specifically where this
should go. And a lot of that is a very
uh uh
process. It's very it's very resource
intensive right to create a system like
this. And I know say Ryan Holidayiday
very famous author and in stoicism realm
who was a protege of grav who wrote the
48 laws of power. He's mentioned his
system where he he will read a book. He
he manually highlights everything in the
book and then he goes back through the
book and he manually writes down every
single highlight and then he will go
through that and then process that
highlight. I think perhaps that's what
allows him to produce such extraordinary
work and to be such a deep thinker but
also that's it's very resource
intensive. You know, it's it's not
something that everybody has a lot of
time for. So perhaps that's where these
systems like Obsidian and Rome kind of
come into play where they make the
process of linking ideas easier even
though it's perhaps at the risk of
losing some of that internal creative
thinking around linking these ideas
yourself. Um which can itself spawn some
some new ideas instead of just letting a
system do it for you. Um so I guess the
question is kind of what is the what is
the middle ground? I suppose if you're
somebody like Ryan Holidayiday who you
know his your sole job as a writer then
perhaps you have the time and the
resources to be manually documenting
highlights to be thinking about them and
to maintain a very complex system. Um
I'm wondering where where do you see
your students in this regard? where you
see most people who perhaps they're
entrepreneurs, perhaps they're writers,
perhaps they're they're influencers or
or content creators and they they look
at something like this as being
beneficial to their content creation
process, but they don't have all this
time, you know, and don't want to ex
exude all of their mental energy and
trying to create these relationships
between these different ideas. So, kind
of what do you what do you say there and
what do you recommend? Um, I look at it
slightly differently. Um, I think you
can set up this system
on a weekend and get going. You you're
still learning along the way and you
have to adjust the system and in a way
it never finishes. So, I'm still
learning how to apply it and modify it
to my needs because my thinking develops
and the structure changes. So, uh, it
has an effect on the way I structure my
notes, but the basic setup that allows
you
whenever you have an idea to put them
into a designated space where you know
it's not lost, but can be
used to build something bigger.
that doesn't need more than a weekend or
an extended weekend.
The main difference you describe, I
think, uh, is in regard to what kind of
input you deal with. When Ryan
Holidayiday reads Zenica,
of course, he needs more time uh to go
through a book and ponder about
sentences within the context of the
text.
I like to say when you write a
literature note, so the note that gives
an account of the literature um you're
processing,
I'm often asked, well, what's
what's your regular time? Um am I taking
too long? Am I going too fast through
it? And the correct answer is of course,
well, it it depends on the kind of
literature you're working with. The
appropriate amount to spend on writing a
literature note is somewhere between a
second and a lifetime. I mean there are
people who who read the Bible for all
their year life and still find new
things. And I'm sure Ryan Holidayiday
um has read Zenica um more than once
because he finds new
um angles to it with a different life
experience. Um you often have these
encounters with ideas where you think,
"Yeah, yeah, okay, that's interesting."
And a few years later, you open the book
again and suddenly it hits you, oh, now
I understand. um
with my experience now I I see the depth
and the relevance of that or you read
something and you grasp the idea from
page one. It's actually already in the
title and the rest of the book is just a
variation on the same idea over and over
and over again. So you don't need to
read it twice. maybe just skim through
it all. Um so I think how much time you
have to spend on
um creating the system, developing it,
writing your notes, connecting them
really depends on what you're dealing
with. And there are some some books I
highlight a lot and go through twice
because I feel I can't give a proper
account on what's in there before I
haven't read the the whole bit because
some pieces of information only make
sense after you know what's in the last
chapter and then go back to the
beginning. And then there are articles
like I said where you have all the
information
already in the title.
>> So it's it's possible to spend as I I
love I love what you said, you know, a
second to a lifetime in terms of going
over a note and thinking about uh a
specific idea. And so now we've
mentioned a few times like Rome obsidian
and I believe you now teach a a course
on Obsidian, but before I ask you about
that, I'd love to ask you about kind of
the most common methods that perhaps
people of today can use uh or build a
system like this. I think we have
popular tools like like notion,
Evernotes, Google Docs. I'm wondering is
there uh so say besides Obsidian which I
suppose is probably looked at is like
the the one of the best versions of of
the built based specifically on the
Zillow caston system. Uh do you see the
possibility of using any of these other
tools like Evernote, uh notion, Google
Docs as being able to build such a
system within?
>> Well, some people use them and seem to
be happy with it. Um I can't imagine
myself uh working with
apps that are
not designed for interconnectedness but
where you have to
build your own little workarounds and um
in the end often they apply a similar
system like Luman did where you manually
um ID
um pieces of information and and link
them manually. I feel that distracts me
from uh the content. So I'm extremely
thankful for um the people who developed
Obidian and Rome research just to
um
push the development of these um note
takingaking apps into a new direction.
Um, and
I feel it um it's almost like you um you
take the um foot from the brake and um
it's so much smoother when you can link
and you have the back link and you don't
have to worry about iding and stuff like
that.
So I feel that there was a big shift um
from apps that were mainly designed for
collecting information, storing
information
um
folder based
um and
yeah you can you can certainly do
something with them but um
I feel
there was a breakthrough uh for in the
digital I always struggled um because
there are some elements of the analog
working with pen and paper I I like so
much um I still miss them when I work
digitally but now with this new
generation of apps I feel the advantages
um
are
are so obvious that um the disadvantages
of the digital
um slightly fade in the into the
background. Um you I still miss the
spatiality,
the haptics of it, the
the kind of writing that's really
undistracted.
Um
that you can still do that. Um but it's
but it's then outside of the system. Um,
yeah.
>> Right. And so, Obsidian seems like the
like the main feature. Uh, I'm wondering
if you can describe kind of your use
case or or some of the best cases you've
heard from other people in terms of how
Obsidian specifically uh is is uh one of
the best methods for for helping them to
link ideas. C. Can you kind of describe
like the the visual mapping feature and
kind of what you think really makes
Obsidian itself stand out for for the
Zettocast system?
>> The weird thing is I think the main
reason I like Obsidian is
really hard to describe. It's um it's
just the feeling of being immersed in
your thoughts with it. while I used
wrong research for a while and I liked
it, but I always felt like almost
um distant from it. It's almost like I'm
outside and looking at my notes
and have to apply a more
um prefrontal cortex like approach to it
all and obsidian
um more fades into the background as a
tool and I feel much more immersed in
thoughts. So my my theory is it's
because it allows you to use your screen
better by having multiple notes open by
stacking them by um going more quickly
through different notes
um and thereby having some kind of
orientation.
Um
and the way I teach the title of
customers obsidian
very much tries to
focus on building that kind of
experience of having an orientation
within your notes despite of the chances
to stumbling upon something.
um to get as close as possible to the
original set of customer experience with
pen and paper.
And
>> that needs some
structure
that
um took me a while to figure out. So
Obsidian is not a tool you can open and
just use. Its
main advantage is at the same time its
biggest risk. You can
do almost anything with it and you can
use it in all kinds of ways
and if you don't
have figured out a good structure um
you're lost.
And so what I try to um provide is the
experience-based structure that then
allows you to quickly u focus on your
thoughts instead of thinking too much
about how to set it up, how to structure
it. And
for some it goes a little bit against
the
bottom up approach of the set of custom
where you develop structure from uh from
the bottom up and you collect nodes see
how they fit together and then figure
out okay what's the structure here um
how do these things belong together
because you you already start with some
kind of hierarchy top down,
but it doesn't
um
hardwire anything into this system. You
can always change the structure
when your thinking changes because in a
way the way we think about things is the
way we structure things. So it it needs
to change something that couldn't be
done with a classical folder structure.
Um but I think it's justified because
when people start with
cast and obsidian
they don't start from scratch. Um you
don't have to pretend you know nothing.
You don't structure your thoughts. Um
you have to build it first. We always
already have an idea how we structure
things. Um we have different areas of
interest or different areas of
responsibility.
we um have different questions. So it
makes sense to start at the beginning to
make this structure explicit.
Uh use it as the scaffold you can then
add new ideas onto and change it when it
needs changing. Um and this structure
is something that
in my opinion
um is to some degree an alternative to
the haptic orientation you have with the
analog set.
So in the analog set you always knew
okay um my my notes on on writing and
thinking are somewhere on the left
bottom drawer and um I kind of know how
the notes feel because of
um used them so often or you know it was
a beloved burke you you kind of know
where the things are. um you don't have
that in the digital form but you have
other means of orientation
uh within obsidian.
Some of them are built in
but
most of them you need to create yourself
or use um a preconfigured
uh structure you can then tweak and
adjust to your own needs. Um I think
that's that's the challenge of these
ingenious uh apps that they are so open
uh that at the same time you need to
restrict uh the openness again with your
own
>> ideas. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I think one way of looking at it
perhaps is that Obsidian itself provides
kind of the foundation but then you need
to be the architect and decide you know
how are you going to build on that
foundation and I know I I first time I
tried to use Obsidian I was completely
overwhelmed and I I was like this is way
too much for me because you have to
approach it um it's not it's not like a
tool like Evernote or Google Docs where
everything is kind of laid out and it's
like if you you you know that you're
going to put a note into a folder and or
a notebook and that's that's they they
provide the structure you know they are
the architects of that system and when
it comes to the is having a zilloccast
system whether you're using an analog or
a software version is that you are still
having to develop the structure of how
you are storing this information and now
I think Obsidian and Rome you know they
they try to take some of that out
because I think what allows them to be
so popular is their kind of intuitive
kind of visual linking it's like
birectional linking system where where
you can create these these links that go
between your notes back and forth. And I
love the the mind mapping functionality.
And I think a tool a tool like this is
probably the closest that we can get to
right now of having an interior view of
of your brain. And I think that that's
why it resonates so so much with so many
people because it's the the way that the
structure is oriented is closer to how
we think than I think any other other
method that has you know that we've
thought of up until now. And so that's
why I love when you say that Obsidian it
feels like you're you're viewing into
your brain in a way. Um, and that's
that's if you maintain it and if you're
not kind of uh taken a back and just
decide to to look elsewhere because you
just feel so overwhelmed. And I suppose
that's kind of what your course is
about, right? C, can you kind of explain
explain a little bit about your your
course uh what you teach and who you
think uh should consider uh signing up?
Yeah, I mean first of all the I I agree
that um
it it is the closest maybe to the way we
structure internally. So it is like a
second brain but I see it more as a
dialogue partner and that's how the
course is designed to
um build a dialogue partner along the
way. Um, and I I like the metaphor of
the dialogue partner better than the
second brain metaphor because the second
brain metaphor
um,
it insinuates you you look at yourself.
But when I interact with my subtle cast,
I don't feel like I'm interacting with
myself. like I feel like I'm interacting
with a different entity that challenges
me with information I I I don't remember
and or I remember in the moment um I'm
confronted with it. Uh but these moments
of oh um I think you forgot something
here or um you have written about that
before and in a slightly different way
or I'd take a literature note and um
look up a reference in a paper and say
well I don't understand it like that. So
the authors um I think they got it wrong
and so
yeah so it's more like a dialogue
partner and in the course um I provide
the structure
um so to not have this overwhelming
feeling of oh everything goes
um but okay um
here you have your daily note section
you can use that for fleeting notes.
When you have an idea that pops into
your hatch, just write it down. Um you
can connect it with projects or
questions you already tackling.
Um so it comes with uh the preconfigured
um vault with folders which are not
topic folders um but are functional
folders. Um it comes with a selection of
tags which are useful. It comes with a
selection of queries that allow you to
present yourself open loops, open
questions
in the morning when you open Obsidian
and you know, oh, I can continue working
there. Um, but I don't think that any of
that would be much of much use if you
don't get the explanation um why the
folders are there, why the tags are
there, what the function is, how it
interconnects.
So I hope with the course to explain um
how you can quickly build a habit a
routine of daily writing
into this structure and then adjust it
to your needs. Um, and it seems like
most people just go with the structure
as it is and are able to use it for
academic writing, but also for
um
more
looking things up, um, keeping track of
projects,
um, and having information readily
available. Um
yeah, so I think it's a lot about um
skipping this long process of
figuring stuff out um trying to
um conserve the advantages of the
original set casten in digital form
um
that
the students or users ers don't have to
go through this long iteration process
of um developing a structure that works
not just in the beginning but in the
long term. So I have thousand of notes.
It's pretty complex.
And
some some things I only realized
after I went through this threshold of
10 or 20,000 individual notes where you
realize, oh,
you you need to deal with this
complexity in a way. um that
would have been so much easier if I knew
that in the beginning. Um so I think
that's that's what I hope to achieve
with with this um with this course,
>> right? And I think you've said before
that the moment you stop treating notes
as just storage and start seeing them as
dialogue, your your thinking shifts. And
I think that's that's the powerful
component of uh having a system like
this. It's not necessarily something for
everybody. It's not necessarily
something that's easy to to set up um or
even maintain because it requires
constant effort. You have to have a
habit of regularly creating notes that
are not just notes in terms of quantity
but in in terms of quality and having
some kind of sufficient method or
routine where you are frequently using
this system and that's the only way that
your brain is going to trust this system
to maintain a certain set of outside
knowledge that you will be more likely
to reference. because I've made the
mistake of having say an Evernote system
that I tried to build on Thiago
Thiagoforte's par method. We have
projects, areas, resources, archives and
then I end up just forgetting that it's
there. And my first default if I need
information on a subject was to go to
Google or now it's just to go and create
like a a deep research query inside of
chat GPT and I I haven't necessarily
created a habit of let me look at my
notes first and see what I've read
previously, what thoughts I've created.
It's so easy to just kind of have your
thinking shift to extern externally
looking for it instead of intrinsically
seeing what you already have because
there's a good chance that you're going
to have some golden nuggets in there
that you haven't thought of before.
>> I totally agree. It's not for everyone.
Um, I think anyone who expect to be as
proficient as Lumen and suddenly start
uh creating an output of a few articles
a month um will be disappointed um
because
you still need to read,
think, write
and have the discipline to
um
have a routine of um practicing all
these things.
If you think and take thinking
seriously, if you read things not just
for the joy of reading but with the
intention of using the information and
using the ideas and challenges um a book
or article provides
to
challenge your own thinking, your way of
um looking at the world if if that is
your goal, regardless of the output
you're aiming for, I think
it's a method that can work for all
kinds of different people. Uh you don't
have to be an academic. You don't have
to um have the aim of writing. I think
the
common
advantage is that it allows you to
challenge your own thinking and it's so
much easier to change your thinking when
you have it externalized first. When you
look at your thoughts in writing, it's
so so much easier to detect the flaws in
that or contradictions between two
pieces of uh information you have
written down. You you just detect that
when you look at it. But it's if it's
only in your brain, if you read
something and you think, "Yeah, okay,
that's that's interesting." And then you
read the next bit and you think, "Yeah,
okay, that convinced me as well." you
don't even realize that these two things
don't fit together. So that that is what
it makes it interesting to me. I think
that's what makes it relevant for
writers because if you want to write
something original, you need to
come up with something new, interesting,
a new angle. You need to
um
let ideas
be enriched through your own experience.
Just taking something from CHP and
putting it on paper. Um people will see
that it is not enriched by your
experience. There is a difference
between here's a piece of information. I
know this is true and that is true and
being able to express the relevance of
something and that needs a human
intervention and the settle casten
expands this personal space and uses the
advantage of externalization
to
modify to develop and in in a way to
mature your own thinking.
Um, so I agree it's not for everyone,
but I also think it's it doesn't need to
be this
academic tool that needs attention all
the time. For me actually um that might
surprise you. There are long streaks
where I don't open my settle custom at
all. Um because I'm in the middle of
finishing the online course and have um
organizational things to do. I need to
call people. I I go on podcast. Um
so it's on the back burner. I I'm I
didn't start this day with opening my
subtle custom. Now actually I did
because I for preparation of the podcast
I I I of course looked into it. Um but
but there are long periods where I don't
look at it and
at the same time whenever I have a
sudden idea and I think that's relevant.
I I wouldn't know where to put it if not
into my telecast. Um, if I just put it
somewhere on paper, it it would be lost.
Um, it can be an in between step, but I
need to know it goes there, but because
that's the only place where it can make
an actual difference. Um, so it allows
me to pick up um where I left it, even
if I left it a couple of weeks ago. Um,
I don't know if routine is overrated.
Um, to me, having a daily routine is
often something I
I I really like the idea of, but in
reality, it it it often doesn't work.
I'm I'm I'm on the train and can't have
only my morning routine at my desk.
sometimes
uh it's too noisy at home and I'm at the
office. Um so in in reality
in my life at least I I don't have such
a daily routine uh even though it it
always sounds great. Um but I'm glad I
have a system which provides me with a
kind of structure that allows me to pick
up um where I left it. um continue to
work with a project and sometimes leave
a project for a while, develop another
one further because
I'm easily bored and um want to switch,
which is maybe a reason a lot of people
with ADHD um seem to like the system a
lot. Um
but yeah, that's um the long answer to
um
to to the problem of um who's it for and
who's it not for.
>> Yeah. And perhaps having a routine isn't
necessary as long as you have the the
instinct to open up the app and say add
the relevant information whenever you
come across the idea or the note or the
highlight as quote and that you think is
relevant to your system. So it's the act
of maintaining the system and then
utilizing it when you need to in
relation to the work that you're trying
to accomplish. And I think that's the
only thing that matters as long as
you're not just consistently adding
information to it and then not
referencing it or not using it because
then you're just creating a a bloated
system that you're unlikely to
necessarily use. But but we've mentioned
chat GPT now a few times and now it's
become very widespread different forms
of AI Gemini Claude and I'm wondering
what your thoughts are on the matter in
terms of do you think it could take over
manual note-taking? Do you think that
could become obsolete? Have you seen
your students kind of using AI and do
you think it's something that that could
replace the Zeno castle system or do you
think it might complement it?
>> At the moment we treat chat chipity or
uh AI um
in a way that's too external
and too internal at the same time. So I
think our thinking is
still
very much tied to what philosophers call
the representational
area where we think of the brain um as
an entity that is
um separate from the world.
It's like a processor that uh deals with
the information coming in and then
information goes out again. And only
recently we start understanding the
impact a different kind of thinking
about thinking can have on practical
matters. So if we think about thinking
as something that happens externally as
well as internally that we really think
within our environment with our tools
we
I think shift the whole discussion. Um,
if you think we only think with our
brains, um, you tend to see AI as a
replacement of our thinking process. We,
um,
use AI to think for us instead.
And that's obviously a risk. And if you
think like that, you do that. You stop
thinking for yourself. you let AI do the
work.
But if you think
that thinking happens in an external
space and you want to
keep the
critical approach to the information
you're dealing with, if you want to keep
the experience enriched thinking that
makes any output
uh interesting for other humans, if you
want to develop your own thinking
skills, your own thinking abilities.
Then it becomes all about
the creation of an environment
that is personal
but also external because only in an
external space you can build up
complexity. You can combine more than a
few things.
Um, so AI makes it in my opinion obvious
that we need to create external personal
thinking spaces.
Even more than that, I hope that we
shift the discussion um more towards
the the question of how can we curate
common spaces to think together in like
a third place between the big
information out there that can be
um quickly searched and
presented by AI and our own little tiny
minds uh that have to deal with that. I
think these third spaces will be where
we make the dis. How we curate them, how
we build them, how we think about them
will be the space will be the question
on how we deal with AR like with every
other kind of information overload um we
face at the moment. And the question,
well, will it replace our thinking or
will it um
um increase our ability?
It really depends on how we build these
third spaces. That that's my point of
view.
>> Perhaps a a a way of viewing it is that
AI itself kind of streamlines research.
you know, we can ask it any questions we
want. Uh we can do a deep research
inquiry and then have all of the the
current information on a specific
subject subject. Whether or not it's
100% accurate, it kind of varies, but AI
will never replace deep personal
thought. Now, we can use it as an
external reference to bounce our ideas
off. But more often than not, the way
that you phrase your question to an AI,
it's going to intuitit your underlying
thinking, your underlying reasoning, the
underlying perspective of what you want.
And that's now why we have situations
where we have people who are going into
delusional fantasies because their AI
believes it's God and they are its
worshipper. And open AI itself has had
to employ now psychologists uh
psychotherapists to try to understand
why is this happening because it seems
that if you have a certain level of of
emotional or a kind of a disorder of
sorts mental health issue that you could
be subject to what AI uh the delusions
that AI itself can go down and so if it
can't place deep personal thought that
is more or less kind of critical
thinking skills. So, I think the next
question to ask is, well, why are
critical thinking skills important if
we're in an era with AI that can just
answer all of our questions and do all
of our thinking? And I think my I would
default to now this idea of of prompt
engineering or it's more recently been
referred to now as context engineering
because there's a lot more than just
trying to figure out how you create the
best prompt because now we have AI
agents that are doing complex workflows
and you really have to be able to think
about how is this workflow going to to
work and if you're employed at a job and
especially now millennials or Gen Z's
especially the Gen Z generation are
having a very tough time graduating from
college and getting a job because all of
the low-level jobs are now easily being
able to being taken over by AI. But if
you have the ability to do context
engineering to think about why is how do
I make AI work best in this use case or
if you have uh trauma or mental health
issues and you're wanting to use Chad
GPT as a therapist, how do I best phrase
my conversation in a way where it's not
going to lead me down a delusional
fantasy? Because it's how you talk to an
AI. And I'm sure we've all used AI in a
way where you ask it something and it
gives you a response, but then you but
then you realize, wait, it doesn't have
this additional context. It's missing
something or I don't feel like it's
quite right. And then you respond to it
and you say, oh, what about this? And
then it's like, oh yes, sir, you are
brilliant. This is and it completely
changes its answer. And so I think all
of this comes back down to what I'm
saying is a encompass is that AI can
help us in our our journey for
accomplishing for building for for even
thinking but I think it's a tool just
like everything else and the moment you
start to see AI as something that is
going to replace your need for thinking
for writing for creative thought then
you're going down a dark path because
that could just lead to a delusional
fantasy.
where you're just kind of not creating
anything new and who knows where that
might end up. So I think now more than
ever we need to emphasize the importance
of critical thinking because that is how
you're going to leverage AI to allow you
to get a job to allow you to get ahead
of everybody else who is not able to
leverage the ability to think properly
and then apply that to AI.
>> So that's that's my my two cents. Yeah,
I I totally agree that the way we use it
is is
crucial and that
there is a way to use it like a machine
that replaces your thinking like like a
bicycle you drive to work with instead
of walking. So you can just roll and
don't have to put any effort into it.
But you can use the bicycle as well to
increase your range to discover new
places or to train your muscles and um
to enhance what you have. Um so
certainly it's about how to use it. Um
so there will be certainly
curated
environments um as you describe them.
Some that are
fit for mental health counseling and
some that are fit for um research and
pushing research. You know that to
change your way of thinking about the
world requires more than one piece of
information. But you need to take a lot
of pieces of information into account.
You need some kind of some form of
complexity.
Um
it's not mind-blowing. It's not oh wow
my worldview changed in an instant. It's
more mundane.
that probably that is the kind of buffer
we need to
um deal with the information coming in.
>> When I say critical thinking, I suppose
it's like uh the the ability to stop and
pause and question
>> a particular thought, right? Instead of
just accepting what external information
says or what somebody else or something
says about that. And we we tend now to
default to uh just asking AI for
everything and then just accepting
outright what it says without thinking
about what it's actually saying, just
accepting that information. And you
know, if we're in a world we're just
accepting information from an AI, it
might not always be correct. And it's
been shown it's definitely not always
correct. Um and so that can lead us down
like wrong paths. But I I suppose a a
perspective of utilizing AI in relation
to zetocasten is that perhaps it's it
can be good for summarizing. I don't
know. I I assume that Obsidian hasn't
implemented any AI functionality, but I
assume if they did, it would be helpful
because it's like everything else where
you can build out say like like the
Google uh forgot the the Google podcast.
I'm forgetting the the name of that
where you can upload PDFs of information
and then generate a podcast that will
kind of summarize the information in of
what you've up told it to to specify. So
perhaps I think there could be a benefit
in utilizing AI for that. But overall it
still is that there's a risk of being
overrelyant on AI as a means of of
externalizing your thinking because we
it's still today just as prevalent many
years after it became popular that the
ability to create a a good prompt is
directly proportional to the quality of
the response you're going to get. And if
you have a zettocast and network or a
system where you are able to see all of
these ideas and thoughts and intercon
the interconnectedness of them is going
to give you a different perspective when
you ask that question to AI that is
going to generate a a proportionally
much better response than if you had not
had a system in which you were able to
see all of the connectedness between
various thoughts and ideas. the idea of
critical thinking as stopping,
reflecting, and taking the time to look
at something. And it is connected to
something that is often overlooked. Um,
reflection is not just about judging
information coming in. It's also about
challenging the way we look at the world
and to change and develop mature in our
way of looking at the world and enrich
it with experience. So being able to
realize that the prompt you use is
probably not the best one um but that
you have to add context to it to get a
better response.
Um is only possible if
something on your side on the personal
side has developed over time. Um maybe
we look too much at judging information
coming in and too little about
developing our ability to deal with the
information.
Um so not just about um
not trusting what's coming in but also
being worried that oneself needs um
maybe a little bit more development to
handle uh the information and
being open to have your mind changed by
it.
>> Yeah. And in an area in in in which we
in an area in which AI is a part of our
daily lives, I think it's now important
more important than ever to have a
system where you're able to collect
information because that will be useful
in helping set you apart from everybody
else who's able to use this tool but
using it in a much more generic capacity
without the level of insights that you
might otherwise gain by being able to
maintain your own personal note-taking
system. I think we've seen people like
like Ryan Holidayiday, David Pell,
Thiago Forte, all very prominent figures
in the self-help space who've either
developed a variety of books or systems
based on the Zenoccasten system. So, I
think it it's something that it as
people who have have used it, they
they've cited, you know, it helps them
to think more clearly. It helps with uh
idea retention. uh and you're able to
just get overall kind of more creative
insights from uh areas of work in which
you might not be able to to create or
gain these insights if you had not had
such a system. So I think it's something
that everybody whether you're a business
consultant or a writer or a student uh
everybody should really consider having
um to to some extent because that's
going to be one of the small things that
will help set you apart going into a
world in which AI is just prevalent
everywhere we go.
>> Yeah. I think the question of how can
you distinguish yourself if everyone can
um access
the the huge pool of information out
there. Um
certainly calls for a curated personal
thinking space. Yeah, you're right
there.
>> And so I I I know that you're working on
a new book and I think you started to
scale back and kind of individual
coaching. wondering if you can offer any
kind of insight into your your next
project.
>> Um, it's still in in development. Uh, I
kind of pick up on my academic work, um,
which is a little bit more about
epistemology, but I hope to make a
contribution to what almost seems like
an epistemic crisis at the moment. um
dealing with um a lot of disinformation
and how to be able to
um
deal with that or um set yourself up to
problematic um
uh information environment. And I think
it will have a lot to do with curating
these kinds of shared spaces and how to
think about shared thinking spaces.
Um
yeah, I would like to make a
contribution um to that solution. Um but
it might take a little bit more time.
And and I I can only hope that teaching
kind of notetaking as like a score as a
as a core skill alongside writing and
math could hopefully become part of our
future and education. I can we can only
dream because I think that would help
massively for our ability to to think to
reflect to question um and especially in
a world in which you know an answer is
just a little chat conversation away um
yeah
so I think that's it's a good good spot
to end. um wondering if you have any
kind of practical advice for anybody
listening that that perhaps this
conversation has piqu their interest in
the zero caston system where they might
go uh to kind of learn more about this.
>> Well, what I offer you can find on
techsmartnotes.com.
Um but there is a lot out there
especially the Obsidian community is so
lively and helpful and friendly and
supportive. I think you'll find a lot of
information and um support there. Um
and I wouldn't underestimate
the power of the metaphor of external
thinking. Just thinking differently
about thinking makes a huge difference
in my opinion. um taking more seriously
notetaking and what it can do to support
your uh ideas and thought development
and not just thinking about thinking as
something that goes on in your brain
just as a metaphor. I think it's it's
can be extremely useful. That that
that's my two cents.
>> Well, uh thank you so much Dr. Sank Arns
for joining us and sharing all of this
this practical advice. Uh and if today's
conversation sparked your interest,
definitely check out his book How to
Take Smart Notes or visit his website
takesmartotes.com for more insights and
resources. And of course, thank you for
tuning in to the Mind Hack podcast. I'm
Cody Mlan. I'll catch you in the next
episode.