hey guys ryan gill here with hunt
primitive where we entertain educate and
inspire
and we're working really hard to get you
where you want to be with your own
primitive building and hunting journey
on this channel we do a lot of primitive
builds how to's and hunting videos this
will be a how-to video if it is your
first time in a channel do please
consider subscribing and following along
but
hey what we're going to talk about today
is how to identify
good rocks for napping which napping is
making arrowheads or making knife blades
so i've got a lot of examples here to
share with you guys today because i get
a ton
i mean a ridiculous ton of questions on
how do i find napping rock and what does
good napping rock even look like and you
know what
sometimes i take this for granted
because i've been doing it for so long
that i just assume that people just know
what good napping rock looks like and
that's not the case at all so
i've had to kind of reel it back in a
little bit and say hey let me put this
information out so you know what you're
looking for
when you go out looking for napping rock
in your area
probably one of the first things that i
need to be really upfront about is
good napping rock can be very
tough to find it can be really easy to
find if you live in the perfect place
say like
uh edward's plateau in texas people
would say why would i ever pay for rock
or why would i ever
have to wonder like i just walk in my
yard and pick it up well
that is the anomaly most people don't
have
rock anywhere in their near vicinity
that's actually
good for napping so like native peoples
used to travel
great distances and also trade great
distances for
good sources of rock so there's even
some places say
like uh north and south carolina
especially on the eastern side virginia
georgia all that
all like eastern seaboard like there's
like no
rock in that whole area so they were
sourcing even poor rock and bringing it
into the area like quartzite and
rhyolite and stuff like that
so there there's lots and lots of
different places that don't have good
rock and then you have other places
that don't have rock everywhere but
they've got little isolated
pockets of it but here i'm going to go
through and i'm going to start showing
you
a few examples things to look for and
also things to avoid
so what makes good napping rock well it
comes down to
a very very basic uh thing to look for
it's something that looks glassy or waxy
okay so let's use this an example now
this is again another anomaly okay so
we're talking about
obsidian okay this is volcanic glass you
can look at this immediately and say
this is good for napping this doesn't
occur anywhere in the east
this is stuff like oregon utah down into
mexico
it's volcanic glass you have to go for
areas that are have either have
active volcanoes or extinct volcanoes
but that's where you're going to find it
not super common so no it doesn't exist
in this area but if you've got that
stuff
it's phenomenal rock incredibly sharp
now
you have other places i mentioned the
edwards plateau in texas
before so this is a good example of that
so this is a type of edwards chart which
is
uh a version of petronalis and you can
see it's got a couple inclusions
it's got a couple different colors and
stuff in it and these aren't a big deal
and i knocked this flake already off so
when you
find rock you see how it's glassy
and will break really sharp and clean
if you can knock a piece off and it's
got a knife edge that can
really cut some stuff that's good rock
okay so this is chert
the north american native edwards
plateau chert specifically
a type of amoeba pattern alice and this
is uh heat treated this is a very light
heat treat on it some of it doesn't need
heat treated at all
now i do have a video on heat treating
rock
as well and i will link that down into
the description not gonna lie it's an
old
really crappy video and i'm obnoxious to
listen to because i'm trying to
be some sort of over uh spoken voice on
the whole thing and it sounds ridiculous
but the information's good
so stick with it like i said it's an old
old video but the information is good on
what heat treating is and what heat
treating
does heat treating can take kind of some
crummy rocks and turn them into good
rocks
sometimes but not all the time
okay so then next on the list we've got
something kind of like a coastal plains
chart
where you're going to look at it like
this and say okay well it breaks kind of
clean but you can see it's not super
clean it's got like tear marks it's got
these little inclusions
all over in fossils so this is actually
a raw piece i could make it a little bit
better with heat
but overall this is a decent maybe a
medium
grade type of rock if you find this
it'll certainly nap
you can even see the patina difference
um
you know when this was probably exposed
for quite a long time
you know probably not a huge amount of
time from when it broke off and then
this is what it looks like when it's a
fresh break so they do patina
just even in a couple years you'll get a
a
difference in color and even texture but
it produces a relatively sharp edge
so that's something to look for kind of
a medium grade
but you can't always judge a book by its
cover either because you can pick a
say a rock up from the creek and it
might look like this
right and you say well that's obviously
that's not good rock i can't
i can't do anything with that rock it's
all grainy it's all crappy but when you
crack
open boom probably one of the
best rocks that you can ever nap in the
world
and you know english flint's very very
similar to that polish flint's
french flint so this is a type of
georgetown which is again a part of
edward's plateau
and it is phenomenal rock but you would
never know it to look at it from the
outside
so another one to really consider if you
look at this it is
probably the worst looking rock ever
that you could pick up and say i could
never nap this
this is why you have to go in the woods
and you have to start breaking them now
this is agatized coral
your average creek rock that you find
that's ugly like this when you break it
open is not going to be pretty
but every now and then when you find the
right place
boom that's the stuff you're looking for
see how it went from crummy crap
to immediately glassy and waxy and this
is raw
so whenever if we do put a heat treat on
this the color will pop and it'll get
slicker and even better
so that's one more thing to look for as
well this is found
in south central florida specifically
pasco county
getting harder and harder to come across
because everything is private land
so then there's a ton of other rocks
like creek rocks and cobbles and stuff
that you're like oh well i found stuff
and it was rough on the outside when i
break it open it'll
be good right absolutely not if you
break
a rock open this is what most of your
creek cobbles
and anything that you're gonna find most
places
when you crack it open it's going to
look like that and you'll say can that
heat treat out
nope absolutely not that is too that's
that's we're not even in the same silica
properties
so i get a ton i mean a ton of people
like i can't even stress that enough a
ton of people that'll send me a rock
like this and say
can i make an arrowhead out of this you
know because it's already somewhat flat
and thin
it's in the shape can i turn this into
an arrowhead absolutely not because when
you break it open
it looks like this on the inside that is
a non-nappable
type of rock you can't use it no matter
what kind of heat you put into it sort
of
melting it down into magma
and maybe trying to figure out how to
make obsidian
you can't do it let's just put it that
way okay so then you may even
live in an area that's got phenomenal
rock and you think well i just need to
go out and pick out a piece of flint so
you can take a piece of edwards plateau
flint that you think or shirt that you
think
should be really awesome but then
there's different grades of it
as well so then you pop it open and it
looks like this
it's got a real good up close look how
trashy that is
so many inclusions so many tear marks
can it be used
you know in a very worst case scenario
you can probably knock some
usable flakes off this heat treat them
and get by
but overall that is not good napping
rock
compared to that you can tell the
difference
this is what you're looking for now it
doesn't have to be that color
again this you can tell the difference
when you look at this
it's slick and waxy and beautiful
and this is trashy and grainy
and full of little fractures and all
kinds of stuff that stuff's no good
and it touched just a little bit more on
that you could take some of the
highest grade rock in the world
okay and you can have stuff that is
freeze fractured so even though it is
glassy and it is beautiful rock right
it is so freeze fractured pot littered
and a mess that you will never be able
to nap that
even though that it is just chalk full
of silica
and it comes from a beautiful source
the fact is it's so damaged
from freeze cracking that it is unusable
it'll crumble when you hit it and this
is also what happens if you overheat
rock
if you put too much heat to it in the
heating process it'll start developing
these fractures and spider web all the
way through it
and it'll completely ruin it so the heat
treating process is actually fairly
dangerous within itself
there are then just a couple exceptions
yet to the rule
because you can take a rock like this
this is agatized coral as well
and you can see how rough and trashy it
is
but when we heat treat it and this is
not the norm you normally can't find a
rock that looks like this so like say
where's that other one we picked up
that looks like this and say can i heat
treat that and it'll turn nice no this
one will not do it
there are a few that will look like this
and then when you heat treat them after
you heat treat
them they still look like this until you
break
a piece off let's get the camera to
focus
and you can see how it went from grainy
this one's easier you can actually see
the little coral polyps in here
nicole the fossil the polyp fossils
super neats million and a half year old
coral
so this is what it looks like see how
gnarly that is say i can't do anything
with it
and then you break it and it's slick and
clean so
heat treating can do wonders for a piece
of rock
if it's the right type of rock all right
folks so hopefully this answers a ton of
your questions on what to look for for
different
napping rocks one of the things you can
do is if you say what am i looking for
in my own area i don't even what kind of
rock do we have
instead of sending me a question or
other people questions saying
what kind of rock do we have in our area
what you should do is start looking
around and even go to local museums
and look for artifacts that they have
that are from
the region locally and that will show
you what the
local rock looks like now there are a
couple little
changes or little nuances for different
areas because
what can happen is a rock say
say central alabama's great great
example the rock will be yellow
in its natural form but if it's heat
treated it'll turn
red okay so then what will happen you go
to
a museum that say has a whole bunch of
woodland points and they're all this
like really red waxy look and say where
can i find this i don't i can't find
this stuff anywhere
the rock is actually a little grainier
and it's yellow
but they learn to heat treat it which
makes it slick
and red so sometimes you just gotta get
on the ground
you know put boots on the ground do some
homework really look around
talk to some geologists they'll usually
help you out and let you know if they
found anything in the area that
you know is a high silica type of uh you
know chirp
jasper agate that kind of thing again a
lot of states don't have good napping
rocks some have a phenomenal amount of
napping rock
some have really good honey holes of
rock that nobody even knows that they
are air
there but you have to just get out and
look for them
but again don't pick stuff
up that looks like this and completely
disregard it because on the inside it
could look like this
but once you break it if it looks
like this you know you're onto the right
path because how awesome is but this is
a crappy piece
look for one that looks like this
that's not freeze cracked and a little
trick to that is
dig down underneath the ground so the
stuff you find at the surface has abso
has taken in water over a period of time
and then it freezes
the ice expands and pops the rock and
puts all those fractures
so if you dig down below that level you
might find stuff that has not actually
frozen and popped so that's a little
another little trip
trick for you but all the stuff that
looks like this
and you break it open and it still looks
like this
don't use that stuff okay you can't use
it it doesn't really matter how much
heat you put to it
if you've got something that you think
could be good like the
like the agatized coral and it's a
little bit grainy try the heat treating
process
if it doesn't break smooth and clean
then chances are it's just never going
to work for you
so thanks for following along i hoped
this helped you
get to where you want to be in your own
primitive adventures and thanks for
following along and we'll catch you
on our next adventure