hi this is richard from original
outdoors this is our 2018 updated guide
to UK knife laws for an outdoor context
so we've got a few things to look at
here the first thing is that UK knife
laws can be more than a bit weird to be
honest they're quite restrictive in
terms of what you can carry but also
they're quite vague in the wording so I
want to explain that but the best way to
explain it is just to read it out I know
I'm gonna do something more energetic
than that in a bit don't worry
so basic laws are knives it's illegal to
sell a knife to anyone under 18 unless
it has a folding blade three inches long
7.62 centimetres or less it is illegal
to carry a knife in public without good
reason
unless it has a folding blade with a
cutting edge three inches long or less
carry buy or sell any type of banned
knife use any knife in a threatening way
you need an illegal knife in Scotland 16
to 18 year-olds are allowed to buy
cutlery and kitchen knives lock knives
are not classed as folding knives and
are illegal to carry in public without
good reason lock knives have blades that
can be locked and refolded only by
pressing a button can include multi-tool
multi-tool knives tools that also
contain other devices such as
screwdriver or can opener van nuys in
the UK it's illegal to bring into the UK
cell hire lend or give anyone the
following butterfly knives the fancy
flippy faulty ones disguise knives so
things like a knife disguise in a belt
buckle or lipstick thing that's got a
knife in it or something like that
flick knives or switch blades or
automatic knives gravity knives stealth
knives so a knife or spike not made from
metal so ceramic knives and zombie
knives and 9 for the cutting edge a
serrated edge and images are worth
suggesting it is used for violence
knuckle dusters quite a long list
with an outdoor context though most of
that doesn't apply the second bit of
abandoned weapons part but the first bit
you've read need to be aware of so I
have five knives in front of me
which I carry for my work and have all
been carried in a public place in some
way so the breakpoint is actually here
everything
that side of the line means something
everything that's out of line means
something else this is a Victorinox well
it's a Swiss Army knife it has a folding
non locking blade you just press on the
back and it closes it's sharp its
razor-sharp shaving sharp like well most
of my regular cutting tools but that's
it it has a small blade here as well
which I never really use and it's got
the usual screwdriver can opener
corkscrew tweezers and a toothpick that
kind of thing that's a folding non
locking blade of less than three inches
this is a handmade sheath knife it's
quite long blade this was made for me by
a friend to meet my huge hands and it's
a knife I use most weeks with clients of
one type or another and out here in the
woods and on a few other things this is
a getting on a bit now gerber multi-tool
that i've had to repair and fix the
screws on several times the belt clip
doesn't work has all the usual
multi-tool bits including and not very
long but folding locking blade there's a
small button I have to press there to
close it and open l one of these weird
ones where they've died the handle green
folding it locks with a rotating collar
not a button which is a locking blade
there's debate about whether that class
the same as other locking knives and
this Magnum Boca Boca I don't know it
was a cheap knife but I actually had
this as part of my regular mountain
rescue kids I had two knives that I
carried one was a Gerber folding rope
rescue knife which has a completely
blunt tip and very aggressive serrated
edges in a folding locking blade that
was with my rope kit and then this which
actually lived on most the time on my
radio chest harness
have a chess rig with a VHF radio and
torch and a few other things and then
airwaves SATA thought was carrying one
and then that was tucked into it this is
a folding locking blade with a slight
curve quite a solid blade can be used
one-handed quite easily there's a clip
to hold it and a seatbelt cutter and one
of those hard and presto so you could
use it to break glass to be honest in
rescue terms it was more often used for
getting into cable ties and that kind of
thing
including loaning it to a police officer
so they could cut into their own
equipment to get something out because
they weren't carrying a knife five
knives that I regularly carry I have
other knives I have wood carving knives
or spoon gouges and all sorts of axes
and things but this covers most of the
common uses so that's the break point
there as I read out anything more than
that anything more than a folding
non-locking blade with an edge of less
than three inches I have to have a good
reason as to why I'm carrying it so all
of these here from carrying them in a
public place I need to have a good
reason as to why I have them this as
long as I'm not using it as a weapon as
long as I'm not using it in a way that
can cause alarm or distress to a member
of the public as long as I'm not it can
t be perceived as a weapon then it's up
to a police officer and never do end up
being arrested for carrying that someone
else and the CPS and the courts and
whoever it is down the line to tell me
and to prove why I can't carry that
however it the onus is on me the
pressure is on me to explain why I am
carrying those in that location so
mastering rescues knife well I could
explain why I had it I could explain why
I had it as I handed it to the police
officer because they didn't have a knife
the opinel well it's light and it's
really quite sharp and it's a perfect
sort of skinning cutting knife a very
small game and it's just a nice
lightweight knife the multi-tool well
it's just very very useful as you can
see how battered and scratch this one is
this gets used a lot
I've used it to repair the car of use it
to fix for photographic equipment and
under there's little grub screws on
tripods and things and the mechanical
advantage of those pliers is well it's
difficult to get past being able to cut
through wire with it it's all very
useful and having a cutting tool there
is very useful too and then a fixed
blade knife well it does something that
the others can't and that's give you
confidence that it's not going to close
onto your fingers and cut into tendons
and give you a life-changing injury so a
fixed blade knife is perfect for wood
carving doing some serious cutting work
and skinning and preparing large gang I
can explain why I have those when I'm
using them but I would need a good
reason to carry them just because well I
was out walking yesterday and these are
the same trousers and it's still in my
pocket now when I'm in Tesco or the pub
or whatever but that's not a good reason
laziness is not a defense the same goes
for all of these just having them oh
it's always in my kit and it's always
there isn't a good reason my mountain
rescue knife and that was used if I
lived with my radio chest harness and it
came back into the house to charge the
radios and it was next to my mount and
rescue equipment and it lived in the
back of the car but it was always locked
in the boot and it was never really on
display and it just lived there like the
rest of my rescue equipment
I didn't wander around in the
supermarket or in the pub wearing that
because well I'd look like an idiot but
also I wouldn't have a good reason for
doing it same goes for that same goes
for that knife I need to have a good
reason for why I'm carrying them so if
I'm walking in the mountains I wouldn't
really carry something like this because
it's big and heavy and there's nothing
I'm gonna cut but I need all that kind
of cutting power and that kind of
confidence I'd carry something like that
or that or even maps but if it needed a
fixed blade or a locking blade for
whatever thing I was doing then I'd
carry something like that but I wouldn't
just carry it and then still have it on
my person several days later it goes out
with my walking kit on my mountaineering
kit and it lives in the rucksack it
doesn't live in my pocket generally and
when I'm done with whatever I'm doing it
goes back in the kit store on the shelf
or
in the corner of the living room or
whatever else your kit lives it lives
with it it's not something I generally
carry if I need a day-to-day knife for
small tasks and opening packets and
cutting stringing and that kind of thing
then that does the job and I'm legally
allowed to carry that in the UK but
that's the important break point
anything more than a folding non locking
blade of three inches up to you to
justify why you've got it anything less
than that and it's up to someone else to
tell you why you shouldn't have that
assuming you're not using it as a weapon
or brandishing it or using it to say
you're carrying it for self-defense or
whatever reason that's outlined there
there are some changes that are just
about to come in around knives in the UK
the a lot of it doesn't actually applies
they're an outdoor context because the
things that affect where you can carry
things and what you can carry is
remaining unchanged the big one really
is that up until now you could order a
knife online and there'll be no be some
kind of age verification decoration but
the criticism was that it wasn't being
done properly before you could order a
knife online and say you were over 18
and have it sent to your home address
and yeah that's just how how it would
work what's changing is that you won't
be allowed to sell knives to a home
address it can only go to a business
address so thinking behind that is I
think that prevents people buying knives
quietly and just getting them sent to
their address anonymously under the age
of 18 and then with only a knife without
any much of a trail back to them but
still allowing businesses to order
knives for work and for resale but it
will just kill the mail-order - home
knife industry although what would
probably happen and assuming that this
is still allowed within the law that
people would just get their knives that
they buy online tend to work another
change is that it's going to be illegal
to carry a knife of any kind on a high
risk higher education establishment or
campus
has been a case in schools but it's
going to go to that there are a few of
the changes around the definition of
those illegal weapons and what's illegal
to own and to to buy and that kind of
thing but in an outdoor context is not
actually changing that much the things
that really do affect the outdoor
recreation and professional user have
been the case for a while and will
remain the case folding non locking
blade of less than three inches you can
carry it in generally in a public place
fixed blade locking blades it's up to
you to have a good reason as why you're
carrying that it's probably also worth
thinking about what you're doing in
terms of trespass and things like that
because people while camp and go to find
huge acres of woodland that they can't
really find the landowner maybe go and
have a sneaky overnight in a bitty bag
there and there's the whole micro
adventure thing and getting out of
London and just going sleeping in a baby
bag on the side of the South Downs or
somewhere quietly not disturbing anybody
not causing any problems the landowner
doesn't know you're there and wouldn't
know you have been there because you've
you've followed the practices of Leave
No Trace and you've not had a fire and
you just quietly lay down slept for the
night
take it and photo as a sunrise and
walked off again even though you don't
have the right to camp there it's
technically trespass trespass is just a
civil offense but if you're carrying
that does that make it armed trespass no
doubt that we debate about that in the
comments below and it depends on the
case and whose land you're on and all
those other things but you've got to
think about these things in a wider
context particularly as knives are being
seen less and less by the general public
as tools and more as well weapons knives
because that's how they're being talked
about by the media by politicians and by
everyone else for me these knives are
all tools they are five very useful
tools to me and they are as useful as my
rucksacks and my sleeping bags my tents
and my ropes and my kayak and my canoe
and my mountain bike my camera equipment
my water proofs
their tools their tools that can be
misused and the tools that I need to
take care of and they'll take care of me
so that's the end of it really that's
the end of the basics of UK knife law is
not changing a great deal for an outdoor
user but you should be aware of where
that break point is between the folding
non-locking blade of less than 3 inches
and everything else why you have a good
reason about carrying it so that's the
end of the knife law section I'm going
to go to the next bit which is my
opinion on the whole thing so if you
don't watch that you can turn off now
thank you for watching
but if I want to see my opinion then
keep watching ok so that was a law bit
this is my personal opinion because I
don't really talk about in the tutorial
videos you know we laugh and joke and
say things but we don't I don't really
talk about my views on political matters
and cultural matters and other things
but I think in this case it's
appropriate to because well the last
time this isn't the first video on
knives that I've made for this channel
the last time we made a video it was a
short simple video very similar mine's
on the table talking about can you carry
this can you carry that and all sorts of
things that video led to more comments
on the channel than anything else we put
online they look something like this and
that video also led to people
well contacted me at work because this
is this is a YouTube channel but it's
the YouTube channel of my business of
original outdoors and run training
courses and have clients and have an
office and all sorts of things which are
linked to from the channel the website
is easy to find and I meet him a real
name people were finding me at work and
contacting work to not to discuss
courses or to inquire about things but
to discuss that video in particular
because they for some reason disagreed
with something in that and the video was
pretty much the same we read out the
laws talk about the knives fault in
non-locking less than 3 inches that's
about it but people feel very
passionately about this subject and not
only did they call work but they arrived
there and arrived to the office which is
interesting when somebody suddenly
arrives at your place of work a complete
stranger and once this
their opinions on knives and
self-defense with you that's a weird one
so I want to address that in this video
so there are various lives here the vat
knives I use an outdoor setting and two
others I grew up in a rural house and
Rahl family and we had firearms in the
house and we had firearms relatives
houses and most of my family of owned
guns and one type or another and were
also serving police officers and worked
within the law or the Armed Forces or
various other things and were hunters
and farmers and working outdoors and
worked in the countryside and had their
firearms there as a tool of their
business or as a sporting tool they
weren't really seen as weapons they
weren't there for self-defense they were
there as a tool but throughout the 80s
and into the 90s various incidents
happened and very tragic incidents that
led to the UK laws on firearms changing
so it went through the point so there
were various amnesties at that time
which my family then just did what
everyone else did every other
law-abiding firearms owner and just
handing everything in because you didn't
really have much of a choice because the
penalties for not doing so was so high
that's that was it so that's what
changed and alongside all that we've
used knives we use cutting tools in the
same way that I do every day now and
that no doubt my children will if they
follow me into this career or doing
something similar to it so knives are
part of my everyday life but it's also
part of other people's lives everyday
for different reasons
you can't argue that the knife crimes
and violent crimes involving knives has
gone up in the UK in the last in a
recent period mostly around London
mostly or other large urban areas in the
UK and I think knife crime in rural
areas like this actually increased that
much and it's the definition of that
live crime it's not necessarily people
stabbing each other or threatening each
other or cutting each other
it could be someone illegally carrying a
knife
or not having a good reason for carrying
a lock knife in a public place as part
of another crime they were committing I
mean that when you look at the
statistics if you take out those kind of
things where some woman was in
possession of an offensive weapon or a
legal knife because they didn't have a
good reason for it
then that drops the crime rate and the
perceived crime rate down quite a bit
but I can't argue that those those
figures those numbers have gone up and I
live in a rural area I live somewhere
without streetlights and where you can
walk outside at night and all you can
see is stars I live in a completely
different place to London in two big
urban areas so I don't have much
experience of what it's like living
there
I carry knives for work legally but I
don't think the way that knives are
portrayed in the media and the news and
the discussion about knives from more
mostly driven by people who live and
work in towns because that's what most
people do live and work if you're not
used to knives if you're not used to
carrying knives as a tool for everyday
use in an outdoor context and talk to
most the farmers around here they'll
have something like that
in their pocket I mean some of the
farmers I know they're probably carrying
it for the day the accent I get their
arm trapped in the baler and they've got
to cut it off by hand that's what the
like around here the most if you're not
useful working with knives and melt as a
tool if your only experience with knives
are either the quite scary stories
coming in about knife crime on the rise
and all these violent crimes and just as
something in your kitchen that lives
next to your toaster and your chopping
boards then something like that can be
seated being quite scary and I've had
this on courses and some media things
when I've been doing some work on TV
where I've said only the knife for that
and I pulled the knife out and once had
to produce the sort of rock back in
shock he said that's illegal you can't
carry that and actually explain - yeah
yeah in this context I can
if you're not used to seeing knives then
any knife is a potentially scary thing
and I think rather than educating people
that some knives are tools and that's
rather than restricting access to knives
and the way you can get them and the
changes and how they're delivered and
you can't have them delivered to your
house and zero tolerance and every other
emotive thing that people say about
knives in the UK at the moment rather
than restricting that access and making
everything into a weapon or to be seen
as a weapon I think what we should be
doing instead is addressing why people
are carrying knives as weapons
this tiny minority that are carrying
knives why are they doing that why they
so afraid that they feel they need a
knife as a self-defense item because
well talk to anyone who does stuff in
self-defense and that kind of training a
knife is a terrible weapon for
self-defense anyway knife fighting and
it doesn't work like it does in films if
you're carrying a knife for self defense
against someone else with a knife you're
both gonna end up being cousin stabbed
it's not gonna go well so and life is a
terrible weapon for self-defense anyway
and if you're carrying it it's not the
item you're carrying this a problem it's
your motivation for doing it it's your
if you're carrying it for self-defense
or to harm someone else well tackle why
that person feels a need to defend
themselves in that way why they feel
afraid enough that something could
happen that they need to defend
themselves or that they want to attack
someone else
I think violent tendencies are part of
human nature but so are many other
things and we've managed to create a
society where we can overcome a lot of
those tendencies throw through rule of
law tackling the reasons why people want
to carry knives isn't easy and I don't
really have any quick answers but I
suspect it takes longer than the average
election cycle and it takes longer much
much longer than the well the several
hours that is a new cycle now people
want responses from the police from
politicians
and from the people that we elect and
have to make decisions for us people
demand responses from them and they want
responses to a perceived problem quite
quickly if you say right we're gonna
tackle the problems in this community or
as a as a nation as a whole that we
think we have and it's going to take 25
years no one's really going to vote for
that or that's not going to survive
beyond the next election because most
long-term plans don't people want to be
able to feel like they're had a response
to a problem quite quickly and
politicians whether through desire or
just because that's the world they have
to work in have to respond to well quick
quick questions with quick answers and
they have to feel like they have to show
that they've done something and I think
that the changes in UK knife law aren't
gonna make it much of a difference where
there is a problem with violent life
crime but it is going to affect people
who knife makers and people who buy
knives and buy well this was from a
friend and I went to his house to
collect this after he made it for me but
if I'd bought a knife from Ben or food
or one of the other many fantastic
craftspeople we have making knives here
in the UK I'd have had to have that
delivered to my office address not my
home address it just added a step in
there that was an inconvenience to me
and could potentially reduce the number
of sales for the crafts person who's
built a successful small business
providing income back into the economy
around their craft it might reduce their
sales as well so the changes in the law
are going to affect people like that and
people who buy knives for outdoor
recreation and for work and people who
sell them as part of their business I
don't think it's going to affect people
in well people who are committing
violent crime because rather than buying
a weird zombie killer knife or something
else they're probably just going to keep
using stuff like this which is a kitchen
knife this is one of my knives from home
it's not even a very good knife these
are my good knives not allowed to take
those out of the house apparently this
is the cheap set of knives I think the
whole knife block cost less than 10
pounds and the front of supermarket and
they're good backup knives for doing
things that I don't want to put my
nicely
it's dropped and honed knives anywhere
near but of all the knives on this table
if we want to be if the one I would want
to be stabbed by the least is that one
the cheapest one here it's a fixed blade
knife I don't have a good reason for
carrying it but I'm guessing that you
have something similar to that at home
it's cheap steel is very cheap steel
very cheap mass-produced produce but
being stabbed like that well that's
gonna give you a very large wound and it
goes in a long way
pretty much goes from one side of me to
the other you still can't get that sent
to a home address through mail order now
but you could steal one from every
kitchen I could also come under
criticism for well I'm not living
somewhere with an violent life crime
issue and where do I have much right to
discuss what's happening
in London and other cities where life
crime is potentially an issue do
standing here in a remote woodland in
North Wales where life crime isn't a
problem sheep rustlers and sheep
worrying is actually more of a problem
here
do I have much for right to talk about
that well if you come along on one of
the courses and you ask me nicely I
might take my shirt off to show you and
you ask me that question
to show you the scar I have here on my
shoulder there across the top of my
pectoral and down here on my ribcage
that was from about just over ten years
ago now where I was attacked whilst
intervening in someone kicking his
girlfriend to death in a pub car park
somewhere in rural Shropshire I was
coming walking past not drinking not
doing anything just happened to be
walking past and I saw something
happening I went over to intervene and
the guy turned round with a knife in his
hand and slashed me across my chest
there stitches and all sorts of things
and I was doing with something well
almost identical to this it was a one of
these retractable stanley knife type
blades he'd stolen that from work it was
something it was something he acquired
anonymously and could ditch and he had
it in his hand for the expressed
purposes of injuring somebody
and so I've been a victim of knife crime
I have injuries I have a scar probably
for life I mean I don't take my shirt
off in public that often so I don't get
much of a tan but when I do get a tan
and I've had been working somewhere
where my skin starts to get brown I've
got a nice pale line here most of it's
covered under chest hair and things but
it is there if you come and see me in
person I'll show it to you but I was
done well with the equivalent to kitchen
knife it was a cheap disposable blade
that he had access to anonymously that
was there part of his work and if you
wanted a knife to cause a crime to
commit a violent crime with he had
access to one had nothing to do with an
outdoor context and carrying that in
your rucksack whilst getting on the
train to go and do some Hill walking in
the late district and that's part of the
problem because decisions are made in
cities by people who don't tend to do
much Hill walking although our current
prime minister apparently is a key in
Hill Walker and guessing she doesn't
carry something like that man changes in
UK law and making knives the access
denies more restrictive I don't think
he's going to make a blind bit of
difference because if that was well that
happened again tomorrow
the guy who slashed me could still
access that from work and still steal a
knife from the kitchen the problems with
knife crime arm the knives the problems
with knife crime are the reasons people
are carrying them and that's what we
need to address not the tools so thank
you for watching if that was a slightly
different video to normal to our other
tutorials but that's what we do as a
channel mostly tutorials I original
outdoors it's a training and outdoor
skills company or based up here in North
Wales on the edge of Snowdonia if you
have a look at the website there's all
sorts of courses and there's blogs on
there
on the YouTube channel it's mostly
tutorials gear reviews and some trip
reports and things but there's more
stuff going on there all the time
that's what I do from work that's what
the video was if you manage to make it
all the way to the end thank you very
much for sticking around through my
waffling
and yeah if you want to like this video
and subscribe to the channel and share
it with other people that would be great
if you want to share it on forums and
Facebook and if you think other people
will find this useful or want to discuss
it that's great you can do that but if
you just watch this and then go onto the
next video then that's fine too
again thank you for watching I'll see
you again next time
[Music]