If you think brains we only
you think tend to with our
see replacement AI as a of
use our AI thinking to process
think We for And us that's
instead obviously think a risk like
And that if you you do
thinking that for yourself You stop
You let work AI do the
Mind Hack is a psychology podcast
about behind the change performance and
behavior self optimization Each episode explores
clearly how to work think smarter
intentionally and live through conversations insightful
entrepreneurs with leading in scientists human
and behavior experts
Hello and welcome Podcast to the
the show Mind where Hack science
we explore of the peak and
performance personal mindset growth Mlan I'm
and your today host I'm Cody
joined Arn a by distinguished Dr
Sank scientist social educator social and
groundbreaking author of the bestseller Smart
Notes How to His Take book
which the powerful introduced Zettocast personal
method knowledge of 100 management 000
readers to over worldwide fundamentally has
challenged traditional some of views the
think on and how write we
learn Dr Rens writing argues is
not that just our a thoughts
way to document It is itself
the act A of concept thinking
that reshaped has profoundly my own
approach work to In intellectual this
conversation demystify the zetocasten will described
approach as building often a explore
second its brain practical and overcoming
power in common roadblocks intellectual like
writer's procrastination block overload and We'll
information also discuss sees modern how
Dr tools RN artificial like Obsidian
intelligence and future fitting of into
effective the learning note By taking
the end and you'll of this
walk episode away with insights clear
and actionable relatable you strategies can
apply that immediately you're looking whether
to performance enhance academic streamline process
or your spark research novel next
major ideas creative for your project
further ado please So without welcome
Dr Shank Ar Thank you Dr
Cody Arves for having welcome me
your to book the How show
to So Take your Smart resonated
Notes with so it's many world
people You've around sold the over
You've 100 000 translated copies into
Did eight you ever languages expect
notes your book would on taking
become Um so I widespread had
two thoughts I sell one a
is few hopefully more than uh
I 10 have copies I had
and mainly mind my because own
students I couldn't in helpful find
book a on really writing that
and mirrors notetaking the developed way
I thought a thesis we So
there a need to was write
just that feel because comfortable I
didn't with available the ones that
I were did it not resonated
expect at so all much that
with of people outside academia um I'm very And
pleased how ideas people and developed
took around their it own So
systems I instruction see it less
as and an more sparked as
something a discussion that I'm happening really
glad um And so Yeah for
those who book haven't can read
you your immediate give us kind
idea about of an what what
it's kind about of and benefits
adopters could that expect say to
new to your learn from Yeah
method I mean there describe are
multiple ways what to about the
tetra Um one cousin way is
is it's all um to a
system write notes that connect in
build a something way that you
out can of you them have
and as you where called brain
it or the an second external
brain dialogue you're with Another in
a it way to and describe
that's is how um I did
the it author in the book
and Nicholas social Luman scientist I
studied he's a system the most
theory um thinker incredibly um he
productive was 60 books um and
writing less than almost 30 years
of hundreds articles and um whenever
he was was asked earth he
um was how able to on
be um that he productive referred
to his obviously subtle cousin uh
as So someone lot who with
struggled writing a I this was
system intrigued is all about uh
what and there research project is
a still it's going such a
on because vast amount needs of
to notes be digitalized that put
and online um but there Um
was very at little that available
time Um uh but who there
work with are others similar so
methods I tried and um to
how that understand really worked in
manner a practical that was fascinating and to
me and wanted um to so
write I about wasn't that because
anything there described available that the
really method the and same because
time I taught at um a
learning lot about theories how I
much the realized settle casten research
put modern into practice probably without
being lumen aware and thirdly of
that it resonates Um but with
line um a of new that
research often goes under the label
thinking of external realization So how
the much of our environment contributes to
our thinking processes we and how
much can to do improve our
thinking little by bit thinking more
systematically a we design about our
how think environment Um in so
which in we a a way
thinking it's all environment about design
that might sound And complicated end
but in the writing it's on
a just daily or regular small
basis and pieces add them to
pool of the ideas existing you
have So your thoughts you extend
instead of them just collecting And
nudges that develop you more complex
to thoughts having the because thoughts
externalized you to allows build impossible up
complexity in which our is tiny
also brain constantly And confronts it
things you you with have And
long that forgotten is like um
a critical builtin element to writing
your Um daily where of you're
things being that might reminded be
um to contradictory your great idea
morning you had in and the
instead out um of just you
putting contrast it that you with
have something already written these down
are the And moments something usually
interesting where happens have contradicting where
you figure ideas out and well
have to um or is can
one I of um them combine
wrong them Um in all in
these a way things you have
a only system happen in place
when have where your you thoughts
externalized in some And way usually
with books we do that and
external articles to all our that
brain is do But we what
usually we just then do it's
in like our brain brain So
and environment the external and that
seat the custom personal expands thinking
to be able to space think
within think that's that and why
I Lumman only be was so
able proficient to not also in
be his writing able to but
develop complex incredibly thoughts and highly
theories consistent that um are within
uh its something itself that wouldn't
that be without possible I a
think system Right So like there's
that this other sure thing you're
I'm you're commonplace aware of book
called it's it's the in been
history famous for Benjamin for many
writers Franklin included is that they
commonplace they created book a where different
they references would note quotes they
would ideas that kind the of
rest keep of with their them
for lives always and an that
important was writing part process of
their Would zodoccasted you say that
method the more is complex kind
of version like a instead of
that of where just writing also
ideas connecting you're related I thoughts
think certainly um it's fits of
into trying the same to category
use external accompany means you and
to um not something just write
down put it back out and
to then the go But blank
the settle page cousin geared is
certainly towards more ideas continuous and
maybe development less of a of
reminder and um um I mean
it's grounded in seeing academia but
how academia much it I resonated
think it outside can of be
maybe seen as a little um
version bit more sophisticated of the
commonplace tell me um book you
know But better you uh I
distinction think the between systems these
two No I I would certainly nuanced
say complex it's a version more
book of and a yet commonplace
it's also more maintain difficult and
that's to systems where like certain
Obsidian Rome and have other kind
of like come the out past
in few many of years easy
to to uh try create to make these it
between relationships different ideas kind in
of doing automatically so I think
but in they the also process
eliminate intentional your own connection ideas
that between perhaps these is some
kind of of the removes critical
making thinking these behind connections because
yourselves I think uh there's what
you this aspect argues of you
writing say in is the not
book just but a the record
act of of thought thinking you
itself argue and that so this
you method to to think is
a about way for these it's
it's things commonly and notated obviously
that thinking whether about you're something
listening book whether to an you're
audio something you're reading is that
remember we we 95 often of
what don't we read but it's
in those a book moments across
when an you idea you come
pause about and that you thought
think you from think a different
about it angle how does you
this think apply about to expand
my on life that you idea
you those of things are the
that types we tend so to
when remember you're and taking that
instinctual that that part kind where
stopping you're and you're something thinking
about and you're system adding then
it you to can a look
expand at on that that and
further that certainly And so I
think writing plays and an active
note taking part of so thinking
I think Um everything and but
um has going its off place
of going Um on uh do
a you tangent have any on
additional top of thoughts that an
Yeah important I think you point
strike on and the um let
role me of comment technology Rome
research like etc obsidian Um I
the think risk there that you
is do just exactly said Um
what automate you connection the building
and therefore of important just step
skip of the thinking connections about
what intellectually make most sense or
by think reasoning this kind But
of technology I have doesn't um
to be used in that way technology I
think that um can complement um
our thinking very well aware if
of we the risk are you
we mentioned try to um use
that it skips in a way
the that thinking that it part
you I use think Obsidian when
or lock Rome and the research
other or tools have the out
birectional there that linking um feature
you get quickly overwhelmed when with
you links automate go that by
process association or like just um
appears oh in this these word
all notes and So I I
have link uh them beautiful a
lot of graphs links with that
can work as a warning this
overwhelming signal interconnectedness um Um if
you encounter you're that once I
think thrown uh the inside back
that any to links deliberate should
be and ideally commented on Um
so points one of I the
keep main uh
stressing method when I is teach
try to the embed notes links
in full to sentences other the
Try relation to between explain two
notes that in your a way
future understand self that can Um
still don't have try bullet to
points just um with um They
have links their place main links
as well but should the yourself
be explained And usually to where
this you is start the moment
thinking intuitively u because often um
between the two relation pieces obvious
of information um you is feel
belongs yeah of together course but
this when make you try it
to you explicit start to usually
struggle the and good that kind
is of first struggle of all
you Um might it's be good
right to and be then because
able to in explain the end
it your knowledge much worth isn't
if you're communicate not able it
to um someone if you else
can't how two things tell each belong
to But other most often you
realize you haven't really that thought
how through two pieces um of
together information belong and information that
you need to more make plausible
the connection So I think um
this can linking be done which
mostly uh if automatic you do
it manually okay um where it's
you interesting feel can here zoom
the most interesting in parts you're
of doing of So what I
not think the linking is support a or
help I think most important it's
often part the of the and
whole the process most interesting right
and I I would in describing a
easier that way of I say
think if if you we are
look a at surgeon perhaps and
on the then side to you're
paint um you or also you
like you're completely in some other
unrelated often field the the people
and it's who multitude end up
in of a fields and they're
that have able interests to take
those overlap ideas them with this
and other profession other and that's
have often innovations where and we
we kind have of ideas further
that society you have along overlapping
because uh different knowledge industries in
these and so this I idea
think of linking kind of notes
like it's a you're similar way
creating of you're this between this
notes this and link thoughts otherwise
that perhaps could forcing be unrelated
yourself It's to specific think idea
about in a a different a
of just way looking instead at
it in way which a in
is a so linear often especially
what we do when bullet we're
points just creating when if highlights
if we have on a we're
book you putting know we're it
category into a and specific then
we it's put a category you
know on if productivity of these
notes all all might this one
just just one be category in
inevitably but there's related ideas I philosophical
industry ideas think that you about
could and allows that could you
be to what have thinking kind
of and to new write creative
and a and different think from
perspective people would than most Yeah
other I think to the art
is um find the right level
Um of on abstraction a two
abstract um level is everything related
if you And try uh to
the abstraction find the level uh
where until two information now unconnected
can pieces be of put you
together create something Um you new
especially and interdisciplinary when you work
different and into fields very like
um medicine you need and to
art go level to a but
more then abstract also to um
respppecify from that level concrete down
to example have or a uh
that application idea I think of
that's are extremely where models useful
place and have because their models
abstractions are always from reality extremely
but useful they uh that because
abstract they are that not you
with can't them anymore do anything
You on can a reapply more
concrete them level yeah sometimes Um
people bit from shy too away
abstract a little ideas ideas or
abstract but unavoidable I think to
it's go often that step um
to to a more go concrete
back level different in a Um
yeah field that that's getting certainly
interesting what's Yeah And and so you also are
say only that as valuable notes
as they're the system embedded that
in perspective And so of from
of a building system a zetocasten
I know Obsidian that we and
we Rome touched and u on
I Lumen believe you know he
uh he had cards these right
index And write so he over
was 60 able to books articles
uh and hundreds he of had
90 like 000 I index think
cards some And specific there's method
a very of notations of putting
in like the upper to right
to link hand corner like should
specifically go And where a lot
this of uh that is a
very uh process It's very intensive
it's very resource right to this
create And a I system know
like say very famous Ryan Holidayiday
author and who in was stoicism
a protege realm of 48 grav
laws who of wrote power the
He's system mentioned where he his
he he will manually read highlights
a book He everything book and
in then the he book goes
and back he through manually the
writes single down highlight every and
through then he that will go
and highlight then process I think
that allows perhaps him that's to
what produce work and such extraordinary to
be such a also deep that's
thinker it's but very intensive resource
You something know it's it's that
not everybody time for So has
perhaps a lot that's of systems
where like these Obsidian come and
into Rome kind play of where
process of linking make the ideas
they
though easier it's perhaps even at
losing the some risk of of
that thinking internal creative around yourself
linking Um these which ideas can
itself some new ideas spawn instead
some system of just do letting
it for a you Um question
so I is guess kind of
the what is the middle the
what ground is I somebody suppose
like if you're Ryan Holidayiday know
his your sole who job you
as perhaps a writer then you
resources have the time to be
and manually the highlights documenting to
to be thinking maintain about a
them very and complex I'm wondering
system where Um where your students
do you in see this see
regard most where people you who
entrepreneurs perhaps they're perhaps perhaps they're
writers they're or they're content influencers
creators or and at something they
they look like beneficial this as
being to their process content but
creation they don't time you have
know all and this don't exude
want all to of their ex
trying mental to energy create and
these between relationships these different of
what ideas do So you kind
what what do do you you
say recommend there and Um slightly
I look differently at it can
Um I set think you up
on a this weekend system and
get going still You you're learning
have along to adjust the way
the and system you it and
never in a finishes way learning
So how I'm to still apply
to it my and modify needs
it because and the my structure
thinking develops changes has an So
effect uh it on notes the
way but I the structure basic
setup my you that allows whenever
you have an into idea a
to designated put them it's space
not where lost you know but
used to can build be something
that doesn't need bigger more than
a an weekend extended or The
weekend main difference think you uh
is describe in regard I input
to what kind you of deal
Holidayiday with When Ryan of reads course
Zenica he needs through more time
a uh book to and go
ponder sentences about within the text
context of the I like to say literature when
you write note so a the
an account note that of the
gives literature processing um you're I'm
often asked what's well your regular
what's time Um too am long
I Am taking I going it
And the too correct fast through
answer well is it of it
course depends literature on the kind
you're of appropriate working amount with
The to spend literature on writing
note is a somewhere second and
between a lifetime a people I
mean there who who are read
their the Bible year for life
all and things still And find
I'm new sure um Ryan has
Holidayiday read Zenica because um more
than he once finds um angles
to it with experience a different
new
Um you life often encounters have
with these ideas Yeah where yeah
you okay think that's And interesting
a few years again later and
you suddenly open the book it
I hits you understand oh now
with my experience um now and
I the I see relevance the
depth something of that or and
you you grasp read page the
one It's idea actually from title
already and the in rest the
of variation the book is just
on a the and same over
idea again over and So over
you read don't it need twice
to it maybe all Um so
just I skim think through how
have much time to you spend um
creating the on system writing developing
your notes it connecting really them
depends with And on there what
you're are dealing some some highlight
books a lot I and because
go through I twice feel I
account can't on give what's a
in proper there haven't before read
the I the whole some pieces
bit because of sense information after
only you make know what's chapter
in the and last beginning then
go back And then to there
the like are I articles said
where information you have all the
already in the So it's title it's
possible to spend love as I
I love I what second you
said to you a know a
lifetime over in a terms note
and of going thinking specific about
idea uh And a mentioned so
now a we've few times and
I like believe Rome obsidian you
now on teach Obsidian a a
but course before that I I'd
ask love you about to ask
the you about most common kind
of methods people of that today
perhaps can use uh system or
build like this a I popular
think we tools have Evernotes like
like Google notion Docs there I'm
uh wondering so say besides is
Obsidian suppose which is I probably
the the looked one of at
is the like best the versions
built of based of Zillow specifically
caston system on the Uh possibility
do you see of using the
tools any of these like Evernote other
Docs uh as notion being Google
able to build system such a
Well within some people be use
happy them and with seem it
to Um myself I can't uh
imagine working apps with that not
designed are for interconnectedness where but
you build have your own to
little workarounds in the end often
and um they system apply like
Luman a similar did where um
you manually um ID pieces of
information them manually and and I
link feel from that uh distracts
the content me So thankful I'm
extremely for um the Obidian people
and who developed Rome research um
just to push the development takingaking of
these apps um into note a
Um new direction I feel it and
um it's almost take like the
you um um foot from you
the it's brake so much smoother
and um when and you you
can have link the have back
to link worry and about you
iding don't and that stuff like
So I feel that there was from
a apps big that shift were
mainly um collecting designed for information
information storing um folder um based
and yeah you can you something can
certainly do with I them but
feel um there was a breakthrough digital
uh I for always in the
struggled there are um some because
elements working of with the pen
analog and paper much I um
I I like still so digitally miss
them when I work generation but
now of with apps I this
feel new the advantages um are
are so obvious that um the disadvantages of
the um digital slightly fade background
in the Um you into I
the still spatiality miss the the
haptics of the kind it of
writing the that's undistracted really Um
that you can still do but
that it's Um then outside but
it's of yeah the system Um
Right And so Obsidian like seems the
main like feature the Uh if
I'm you wondering can describe case
kind or of or your some
use of heard the best from
cases other you've people Obsidian in
specifically terms of uh how is
the is best uh methods one
for of for link helping ideas
them C to Can like you
the kind the of visual describe
kind mapping of what feature you
and think Obsidian really itself stand
makes out for Zettocast for the
The weird system thing reason is
I think I the like main
really Obsidian hard to is describe
just the It's feeling um it's
of your being thoughts immersed with
it in wrong while research I
used for it a while but
I and I always liked um
felt distant like almost from it
It's outside almost and like looking
I'm and at have my notes
to apply um prefrontal a cortex
more like all approach and to
it obsidian um more fades into
the tool background and I as
feel a much thoughts more immersed
So in my because my theory
it allows is it's you better
to use by your having screen
multiple stacking notes them by open
um going by through more quickly
different um and thereby notes having
some orientation kind of Um and
the way I teach the customers title
of very obsidian much tries focus
on building to that experience kind
of of having within an your
orientation notes despite to of stumbling the
chances um upon to get something as
close as original possible set to
of the customer pen experience and
with paper And that needs structure
some that um took me a
while Obsidian to is figure not
out a So tool you can
just use and main advantage Its
open
is at biggest the same time
risk its You do almost can
anything use with it it and
in you all can and kinds
if of ways you have figured
don't out a good structure you're um
And so what I try lost to
um provide experience is the based
allows structure you to quickly that
then u thoughts focus instead on
your of about thinking how to
too set much it it up
how to structure And for some
it goes a little the bit
against bottom up approach where of
the you set develop of custom
structure the bottom from up uh
and you from collect how they
nodes fit see together out okay
and what's then figure the structure
how do these here things um
because belong you together you already
kind of start hierarchy with some
but top it down doesn't um
hardwire anything into can this always
system change You when your the
thinking structure changes because way the
way in we think a way
about we structure things is things
the to So change it it
needs something done with a that
classical couldn't be folder Um but
structure I think when it's people
justified start because cast with and
they obsidian don't start from don't
scratch have Um to you pretend
You you don't know nothing structure
you have to your build thoughts
Um it already first have We
an always idea how things we
structure Um we have different interest
or areas different of responsibility areas
of we um have different questions makes
sense So to it start make
at the this beginning structure to
Uh use it explicit as the
scaffold add new ideas you can
onto then and needs change changing
it Um when and it this
is structure something in that my
um is opinion to some degree
an the alternative haptic orientation to
you analog have with the So
in set the analog okay um
set my you my always notes
knew on thinking on writing are
somewhere and bottom drawer on the
and um left I the kind
of notes know how um feel
used because them so often of
or a you beloved know it
burke was you where you kind
the of things know that are
in um you the don't digital
have form other but means you
have of uh orientation within Some
of obsidian them are but built
in most of them you need or to
use create um yourself a preconfigured uh
structure you can adjust then to
tweak your own and needs that's
Um I that's think the ingenious
challenge of uh these apps uh
that that they are at so
the open same restrict time uh
you the openness need again to
own with your ideas Yeah I
Yeah I think one perhaps way
of looking is that at Obsidian
it kind itself of the foundation to but be then
provides
the architect you need and how
decide are you you know foundation going
to and build I know on
I that I tried first to
time use I Obsidian overwhelmed I
was and completely I I was
too like much this for is
me way because approach it you
um have it's to not tool
it's like not Evernote like or
a Google everything Docs where is
kind of like laid if out
you and it's you going you
know to that put you're a
note into a a notebook folder
and and that's or provide that's
the they structure they the architects
you know they are of it
that comes system to and the
when is system having whether a
zilloccast you're using a software an
analog version or having is that
to you develop are still the
structure you are storing of this
how information I think Obsidian and
now and they Rome try you
to know they take because some
of I that think out so
what popular allows is them their
to be kind kind of of
intuitive visual birectional linking linking it's
like system you can where create
where these between these links your
notes that go back love and
the forth the mind And mapping
I And I functionality think a
tool a probably tool like the
this closest is right that now
we of can having get to
an of interior your brain view
of And I why think it
resonates that that's so people so
much because with so many it's
structure the the way is that
oriented the we is think closer
than I to think how method
any other that other has you
thought know that of we've up
until why now I And love
so when that's you say feels
that like Obsidian you're it you're
your brain viewing in into a
that's way Um and if that's you
maintain not kind it of and
uh if taken you're a decide
back to and to just look
elsewhere just feel so because overwhelmed
you that's And I kind suppose
of about what your right course
C is can explain you kind
of a explain little course bit
about uh your what your you
think teach uh and who should
you Yeah consider I mean uh
first signing of up all that the
I I agree it um it
is the closest maybe structure to
the internally way we second So
it brain is like but a
I dialogue see it partner more
as a and course that's how
the is um build designed a
dialogue to way partner Um and
along I I the like the
the dialogue metaphor partner of second
better brain than metaphor the because
brain the second metaphor um it
insinuates you you But when look
I at interact yourself with my
I subtle don't feel cast like
myself like with I with feel
I'm interacting
a like I'm different interacting me
entity with information that challenges I
I and I or don't I
remember remember in the confronted moment
with um it Uh I'm but
of these oh um I moments
think here you or forgot um
something you have written before about
and in that a or slightly
I'd take different a literature way
look up note a reference and
um in well a I paper
don't and say understand the authors
it um like I that think
So and they got it wrong
so yeah so it's partner more
and like in a the dialogue
course the um I provide structure
um so to not have feeling this
overwhelming of oh um everything but
goes okay here you have um
your daily you note can section
use that for When fleeting you
notes have your an hatch idea
that just pops write into can
it connect down Um you it
questions with projects or you Um
already so it comes tackling with
um uh vault the preconfigured with
folders topic which folders are not
folders um but Um are it
functional comes with a tags selection which
are of useful selection It comes
of queries with a that present
allow yourself you to open loops
questions open in the morning when and you
you open Obsidian know oh there
I can continue Um but working
I that don't would think that
be any much of of don't
much get use the explanation if
you um folders why are the
there there why what the the
tags function are interconnects is how
it So I hope with the course how
you to can explain quickly build
um routine a habit of a
daily into this structure writing and
to then your adjust needs Um
it and most it people seems
like just as go it with
is the and structure are able
academic to use writing it for
but um also for more looking
things up um keeping projects track
of um and having information available readily
yeah so I Um think skipping it's
a lot about this long um
figuring process stuff of out um
um conserve trying the to advantages
original set casten of the in
um digital form that the students
or users go ers don't through
have to this of long um
developing iteration a process structure not
that just works in the long
beginning term So I but in
have the thousand It's of pretty
notes And complex some some things
I only after realized I went
through 10 or this 20 threshold 000
individual of notes realize where you
you oh you need complexity to
deal in with a this way
would um have that been so
that much in easier the if
beginning I knew that's Um so
I that's think with what with
I this hope um with to
this achieve course
right And I think you've that
the said moment before you as
stop just treating storage notes and
start dialogue seeing your your them
thinking as I shifts think And
that's component that's the of powerful
uh this having It's a not
system necessarily like everybody something for
It's something not necessarily that's easy
to to even set maintain up
um or because constant it requires
effort habit You have of to
regularly have a are creating not
just notes notes that in but
terms in in of terms quantity
of some quality kind and of
having sufficient routine method where you
or are this frequently system and
using that's your brain the only
is way going that to to
trust maintain this a system certain
knowledge set of that outside you
will be to more reference likely
mistake because of I've having made
say the an that Evernote I
tried system to Thiagoforte's build on
Thiago projects par method areas We
resources have then I archives end
up just and forgetting there And
my that first it's default information
if I on need a Google
subject or was now to it's
go just to to like go
a and a create deep research
chat GPT query and inside I
I of haven't created necessarily a
habit of notes let me first
look at my and previously see
what I've what read thoughts It's
so I've easy created to just
thinking kind of shift have your
to extern looking for externally it
instead of seeing intrinsically what you
already there's have a because good
chance to that have you're some
going golden that nuggets you haven't
in there I thought totally of
before agree Um I It's think
not for anyone everyone who expect
proficient to be as as Lumen
uh and creating suddenly an start
output a month of a few
um articles will be because disappointed
um you still need think to
read and write have the discipline
um to have a routine of um these practicing
all If things you think seriously
and take if thinking you read
things for the joy not of
just reading intention but with the
of using using the the ideas
information and challenges and or um
article a book to provides challenge
your own um thinking looking your
at way the of world your
goal if regardless if that is
you're of the aiming output for
it's I a think method that
kinds can of work different for
all people have Uh you to
don't be to an um academic
have the You aim don't of
writing have the I think common
advantage is that it challenge allows
you your to own thinking much
easier and it's to so change
you have your it thinking externalized
when look first at your When
thoughts you so in so writing much
easier it's to that detect or
the contradictions flaws in pieces between
of uh information written down you
two
You have you when just you
detect look at it that But
only it's in if your it's
brain something if you and read
you think that's that's Yeah interesting
okay read the And next then
you bit okay and that you
think convinced Yeah don't me as
even well realize you don't that
these fit together two things So
that it makes that it is
interesting what to me that's I
think what makes writers it relevant
because for something if you want
to original write come you up
with need something to a new
new interesting angle You um need
to let ideas um be enriched
through your Just own taking experience
something putting it from on paper
CHP and Um people that it
is will not see enriched experience
by your There between is a
here's difference a know piece this
of is information true and I
that being is able true to
and express something the relevance and
that of needs intervention a human
and expands the settle this personal
casten space advantage and uses of
the externalization to modify to develop
and in mature in a way
to your Um own so I
thinking agree but it's I not
also think for everyone it's it
doesn't be need to academic this
tool that needs the time attention For
me actually all um surprise that
might you There where are long
I streaks don't all open my
Um settle because custom at finishing
I'm in the the online middle
course of and organizational have um
call things people to do I
I I need go to on
so it's podcast on the back
Um burner didn't I start I'm
this I day subtle with opening
custom my because Now actually I
I for did preparation I I
I of of course the podcast
looked but into there it Um
are but long look periods where
at I don't it at the
and same time sudden whenever idea
and I I have think a
that's I I wouldn't relevant know
into where my telecast to put
it Um if if not I
somewhere just put on it paper
Um it it can it be
would an in be between lost
need step to know but it
I goes that's there the but
only because place an where actual
it difference can make me Um
to so pick it allows up
um if I where left it
a I couple left of weeks
it ago even Um I don't
know if Um routine to me
is having overrated a daily often
routine something is I I really
I like the reality idea of
it but it in it I'm
often I'm I'm doesn't on the
work train only my and morning
can't routine have sometimes at my
desk uh it's too noisy office
at home Um and I'm so
at in the in in my life reality at
least I a I daily don't
routine have such always uh even
sounds though great it it Um
but have a I'm system glad
which I kind provides of me
structure with a up that um
allows where me to I pick
left work it with um a
continue project and to sometimes a
project for leave a while one
develop further another I'm easily because
bored and um which want to
is switch maybe a with reason
ADHD a um lot seem of
people to like lot the system
a but yeah Um that's um
the long um answer to to
to the problem of um who's who's
it it not for for and
Yeah And perhaps having necessary a
routine as isn't long instinct as
you to have open the up
the the the app relevant and
say information add come across whenever
the you idea or highlight the
note as or quote the relevant
and that you to think your
system is of So maintaining it's
the act the utilizing system and
it when then you relation need
to to the in work to
that accomplish you're trying And I
only think thing that's that the
matters you're as not long just
consistently as information adding to referencing
it and then it not or
then not you're using just it
creating because system a a bloated
that you're necessarily unlikely use But
to but chat we've GPT now
mentioned a few times become and
very now widespread it's of AI
different Gemini Claude forms and what
I'm your wondering thoughts are terms
on the of matter do you
think in manual it could note
take taking over could Do you
think become that your obsolete students
Have kind you of seen using
you think AI it's and something
do replace that the Zeno that
castle could system think or do
it you At might the complement
moment we it treat uh chat
chipity AI or in a um
way that's and too too internal
external at the think same time
So our I thinking still is
very much tied to what philosophers the
representational call area where we think of the an
brain entity um as um that
separate is from It's the like
a world processor the that uh
information deals with information coming in
and then recently goes out we
start again understanding And only the
impact a different about kind thinking
of thinking can matters have on
So practical if we think as
something about thinking that happens well
as externally internally as within that
we our really environment think with
we our tools
I think shift the whole discussion if
you Um think brains we um
only think you tend with to
our see replacement AI as of
our a thinking um process We
use AI to think for And
us that's instead obviously think a
risk like And that if you
you do thinking that for You
yourself stop work you let AI do the
But if you that thinking think
happens space in an external and
you keep want the to critical
approach you're to the information dealing
with the if experience you want
to enriched keep makes thinking that
uh any interesting output for other
want humans to develop if you
skills your own your thinking own
thinking Then abilities it becomes all
the creation about of an that
environment is but also personal external
because external only in space an
complexity you can build You can
combine up few more than a
Um things so AI makes it
in that my we opinion need
to obvious create external thinking personal
Even spaces more than shift that
I the hope discussion that we
the um the more question towards
of how common can spaces we
curate to think a together third
in like place information between out
the there big um that quickly
can be presented searched by AI
and and our minds own little
uh tiny that think have to
these deal third with that spaces
I we will make be the
where dis How we we curate
build them how them will how
be we the think space about
will them on be how the
we question deal with other AR
like kind with of every information
face at overload the moment um
we well And will the it
question replace will our thinking or
it um increase um our It
really ability depends on how third
we build spaces these That that's
view my point of
Perhaps a a a way of AI viewing
itself it kind is of that
streamlines you know we research can
ask it want any Uh questions
we can we do inquiry a
deep and research then have current
all of information the the subject
on a subject specific 100 Whether
accurate or it not kind of
it's varies will never but AI
replace thought deep Now personal we
can external use reference it as
an to off bounce But more
our ideas often that than you
not phrase the way your it's
question going to to an intuitit
AI thinking your underlying your underlying
underlying reasoning perspective the And of
that's what you now want why
where we have we situations have
people delusional who are fantasies going
into because believes their it's AI
God worshipper and they are And
open its AI to itself employ
has now had psychologists psychotherapists to
uh try why to is understand
this happening that if because you
have it a seems certain emotional
level or of a of kind
sorts of a mental disorder health
of be issue subject that to
you what could AI that uh
AI the itself delusions can go
can't down and place so deep
if personal it is thought more
or that less kind of
thinking skills critical So question I
think to the ask next is
critical well thinking why are skills
we're important in an era if
with AI answer that all can
of just our of questions our
thinking and do And all I
default think to my now I
this would idea engineering of of
prompt or it's referred more to
recently now as been context because
engineering there's trying a lot to
more figure than just out best
how prompt you create because the
agents now that we are have
doing AI complex and you workflows
really have to about be able
how to is think this workflow
work and going if you're to
to employed especially at a now
job millennials and especially or Gen
the Z's Gen having Z generation
a very tough are college time
graduating and getting from a the
job low because level all jobs
of are able now to easily
being taken being over you by
have AI the But if ability
engineering to do to context think
I about make AI why work
is how best do in if
this you use have uh case
trauma or or mental issues health
and you're GPT as wanting a
therapist to use Chad how my
do conversation I best in phrase
a way going where it's to
not lead fantasy me down a
Because delusional it's how AI you
And I'm talk sure to we've
an way all where used AI
you in ask a gives it
something you a response and it
but then then you you realize
but this wait it additional doesn't
have context something It's or missing
I don't quite feel right like
it's And and then you you
respond say oh to it what
then about it's this like And
oh brilliant yes sir you This
are is changes and it its
answer completely And so I of
think this comes all saying back
is down a to encompass what
I'm help is us that in
AI our can accomplishing our journey
for for thinking building but for
I for think even like everything
it's a tool else just and
start the moment to see you
AI going as something to replace
that is your for need writing
for thinking for creative you're thought
going down then a that dark
could path just because lead to
a fantasy delusional where you're just
anything kind of new not and
creating who knows might end where
up So that I ever think
we need now to more emphasize
than of critical the importance thinking
you're because going that is to
leverage how to AI get to
a allow job to you allow
of everybody you to get ahead
else who leverage is not the
able ability to and to think
then apply properly So that that's
to AI that's I I my
totally my two agree cents that
Yeah the is way we is
use it crucial there and is a that
way to use that it like
replaces a machine your thinking bicycle
like you like drive a of
to walking work with So instead
you can don't just roll have
and to put But any you
effort can use into it the
increase bicycle as your well range to
places to or discover to train
new to your enhance muscles and
what um you certainly have Um
it's about so how so there
to use will it be Um
certainly curated environments um as you
Some describe them that fit for
mental are health some that counseling
are fit for and um pushing
research research and You know change
that your way to of thinking
world about requires the more information
than one piece But of you
of need to pieces take a
lot of You information need some
kind into of account some form
complexity of Um it's not mind
blowing my worldview It's not changed
oh wow in an more instant
It's that mundane probably that is
the we kind of buffer need
um deal with the to information
coming When I say in critical
it's like thinking uh the I
the suppose ability pause to stop
and and a particular question thought
just accepting right Instead what of
external says or information what somebody
says else about or something that
And we default we to tend
uh now just to asking everything
AI for and outright then just
what accepting it says without about
thinking what it's accepting actually saying
that information just know if And
we're you in accepting a world
information we're just might from an
not AI always it been be
correct shown And it's it's definitely correct
Um not always and so like
that wrong can lead paths us
But down I perspective I suppose
of a utilizing a to zetocasten
AI in relation is that can
perhaps be good it's for it
summarizing know I I I assume don't
implemented that Obsidian any hasn't AI
functionality assume if they but did
I it because would it's be
like helpful everything you can else
build where Google out say uh
forgot like like the the the
Google I'm forgetting podcast where the
the you name can of upload
that and PDFs then of information
generate a kind podcast of summarize
that will the what information you've
up told in it of to
to perhaps specify I think So
in there utilizing could be a
AI benefit for still that But
is overall that it there's overrelyant
a risk on of AI being
as a means externalizing of of
your it's thinking still because today
we just years as prevalent after
it many became ability popular to
create that the a directly a
good proportional prompt is to the
the response quality you're of going
you have to get a And zettocast if
system where you a are these able
and network or
to ideas see all and of
thoughts the interconnectedness and intercon to
of give them you is a
going different you ask perspective that
question when going to AI to
that generate is a much a
better proportionally response than had a
if system you had in not
which see all you of were
the able connectedness to various thoughts
between and ideas critical the idea
thinking of reflecting as stopping and
at taking something the time And
to it look is something connected
that is often to overlooked reflection
is Um not information just about
judging coming challenging in It's also
the about way we and to
look change at the and world
develop mature way of in looking
our it at with the experience world
and enrich So being realize able
that to the prompt probably you
not use the is best you
one have to um add but
context that to it better to
get a Um is response only
possible something if on side your
has side developed on the personal
over we time look too Um
much maybe at judging coming information
in and developing too little our
ability about to deal information with
the Um so not just about not
trusting um what's being coming worried
in but that also oneself maybe
needs a little um handle bit
more development uh the information to
being open to have and your
mind it changed by Yeah And
in an area in in in
in an area which in which
we AI daily is a lives
part of I our think more
it's important now important than system
ever to where have a information you're
able to because collect in that
helping will be set useful you
apart else from who's everybody able
to using use this it in
tool a but much without more
generic the level capacity of might
insights otherwise that you gain maintain
by being your own able to
personal system note I taking think
like we've Ryan seen Holidayiday people
like Thiago David Forte Pell all
very in prominent the self figures
help developed space who've a variety
either of based books on or
the systems Zenoccasten think system it
it's So something I people that
who it have as have they've
used it cited they to you
think know it more helps clearly
them It idea helps retention with
uh uh and just you're get
able overall to insights kind of
from more uh areas creative of
you work might in not which
be able gain to these to
create insights or if such a
you system had not So had
I that think everybody it's something
whether consultant you're or a a
business writer everybody or a student
should uh really um to consider
to some having extent going because
to be that's one of will
the help small set things you
apart world going in into which
that
a everywhere AI is just prevalent
Yeah we I think go the
you question distinguish of yourself how
can if um everyone can access
the the huge pool of there information
out certainly calls Um for a
thinking curated space personal Yeah there you're
right And so I I I know a
that new you're book and working
I think on scale you started
back to and coaching kind of
wondering individual if kind you of
insight can offer into your any
your project next Um it's still
in in kind development of pick
up Uh on I my which
academic work is um a epistemology little
bit more but about I contribution
hope to make to a what
an almost epistemic seems crisis like
at dealing the with moment um
a um lot and of disinformation how
to be um able to deal
with that or um set yourself problematic up
to uh information um environment it
And will I have think a
these lot to kinds do with
of curating shared think spaces about
and shared how to thinking Um
spaces yeah I contribution would like
to um make to a that
it might solution take a little
Um bit but more time And
and I I can only kind
of hope notetaking that teaching as
like as a a score core
skill as a alongside math could
hopefully writing and become future and
part education of our dream I
can we because can only I
massively think that for would our
ability help reflect to to to
question think um to and a
especially world in in just which
a little you know an chat
answer conversation is yeah away um
so I think that's to it's
end a um good wondering good
spot kind if of you practical
have any advice listening for that
anybody that perhaps conversation this has
the piqu their zero interest caston
in go system uh to where
kind of they learn might more
Well what about I offer this
techsmartnotes you can find on Um but there com
is especially a lot out the
Obsidian there community lively and is
helpful so supportive and friendly I
and think information you'll find and
a um lot of support and
there I wouldn't Um the underestimate power
of the metaphor thinking of external
Just thinking about differently thinking makes
in my a huge opinion difference
um notetaking taking more seriously and
what it your can uh do
ideas to support and thought and
not development just thinking about something
thinking that as goes on just
as in a your metaphor brain
I can think be extremely it's
it's that's useful my two That
cents that Well uh thank you so much for
joining Dr Sank us Arns and
this practical sharing all advice of
this Uh conversation and if today's
sparked definitely your interest check Take
out Smart his book Notes How
to or takesmartotes visit his website
com for resources more insights And
of and course tuning thank in
to you the for Mind Cody
Hack Mlan podcast I'll catch I'm
episode you in the next